we believe one in six people are
我们相信六分之一的人是
narcissistic and exposure can become a
自恋者，而暴露于自恋状态可能危及
life or death situation but the key step
生命。但
to identify narcissism is Dr Romney
识别自恋的关键在于罗姆尼·贾萨博士（Romney
jaasa licensed clinical psychologist the
Jaasa），这位持证临床心理学家是
world's leading expert on narcissism all
世界领先的自恋专家。他认为，
narcissism is on a spectrum at the
自恋是一个连续谱，
lowest ends it's Instagram saviors but
低端是像Instagram上的“救世主”那样的人，而
the severe end of the spectrum you're
极端自恋者则像邪教
talking about a cult leader they have
领袖一样。他们缺乏同理
low empathy they will dominate people
心，会支配他人，
they have to get the last word they get
必须争个输赢，而且
angry very quickly and that's just the
很容易发怒。而这仅仅是
iceberg what about the impacts of
冰山一角。那么，
narcissism on relationships narcissistic
自恋对人际关系的影响又是什么呢？自恋
people they can go out in the world and
者在外人面前往往
they're able to be charming and
魅力四射，
relationships start strong they want to
他们渴望
get you quick and then it becomes
迅速俘获你的心，但随后就会变得
dismissiveness manipulation gaslighting
冷漠、操控、煤气灯效应。在
the world thinks this person's fantastic
外人看来，这个人很棒，
a lot of people say aren't you lucky
很多人会说“
that you're married to that guy and
你嫁给了这样的人真幸运”，但在
behind closed doors they psychologically
私底下，他们会从心理上
destroy you narcissism in work how do I
摧毁你。自恋…… 工作中，我如何
know if my boss is a narcissist you're
知道我的老板是不是自恋者？你会
going to feel it in the sense of you
感觉到，比如你感觉
don't feel seen you don't feel valued
不被关注，感觉不被重视，
you feel like the workplace is
感觉工作场所
unpredictable you might even feel that
难以预测，甚至可能感觉
it's psychologically unsafe what about
心理上不安全。那么
world leaders if our adversary in
世界领导人呢？如果我们在
another country is a narcissist would we
另一个国家的对手是自恋者，我们是否更
rather our leader be a narcissist as
希望我们的领导人也是自恋者？
well that's a fantastic question and I
这是一个绝妙的问题，我
think so the big question how do you
认为答案是肯定的。一个重要的问题是：你怎么
know if you are a narcissist and can you
知道自己是不是自恋者？
cure narcissism so here's where we get
自恋可以治愈吗？接下来我们要
into some interesting Muddy
聊一些有趣的事情。Muddy
Waters it's absolutely crazy to me that
Waters，
so many of you have decided to watch our
你们这么多人选择观看我们的
show um and so many of you have decided
节目，这么多人选择
to subscribe to our show we now have
订阅我们的节目，这对我来说简直太不可思议了。我们现在
five million subscribers on YouTube
在YouTube上有500万订阅者，
which is a number that I just can't
这个数字我简直无法想象，这完全是
comprehend and it's a dream that I
我以前想都不敢想的。
absolutely never could have had we
我们
started the dire of a CO just over three
三年前开始制作《Dire of a CO》，
years ago now and in my wildest
即使我最乐观的
expectations we might have had 100,000
预期，我们也只能做到这样。 现在我们已经有10万
subscribers by now so you can imagine
订阅用户了，所以你们可以想象
how shocked I am that so many of you
我有多么惊讶，竟然有这么多人
have chosen to tune into these
选择每周收听我们的节目，花
some time with us so thank you and I
时间和我们一起聊天。非常感谢你们！
made a deal with you I made a deal that
我和你们达成了一个协议：
if you subscribe to the show that we
如果你们订阅我们的节目，我们
would continue to raise the bar and in
会不断提升节目的质量。
2024 we're going to raise the bar like
2024年，我们将把节目提升到
never before I've been working for the
前所未有的高度。
last N9 months on a surprise for all of
过去9个月，我一直在为所有订阅用户准备一个惊喜，
I'm very excited to deliver that for you
我非常激动地要把它呈现给大家。节目的
the production's going to change we're
制作方式将会改变，我们会
going to go even further with our guests
与嘉宾进行更深入的交流，
and we're going to tell even more Global
讲述更多全球性的
stories so as always if you appreciate
故事。所以，和以往一样，如果你喜欢
what we're doing here the simple free
我们在这里所做的一切，
favor I'll ask from you is to hit the
我唯一的请求就是点击
Subscribe button let's get on with the
订阅按钮。让我们开始今天的
[Music]
[音乐]
episode Dr Romany mhm you've committed
节目吧。罗曼尼博士，嗯，您投入了
so much of your life and your energy to
大量的时间和精力研究
narcissism why does it matter oh it
自恋这个主题，为什么它如此重要？哦，它
matters so much because exposure to
非常重要，因为接触那些
people who have narcissistic
有自恋倾向的人…… 自恋型
personalities
人格会
shapes how people's identity develops
影响人们身份认同的形成，也会影响
shapes how their personality develops or
他们的性格发展。
if the first time you encounter a
如果你
narcissistic person is in adulthood it
在成年后才第一次遇到自恋型人格，它
can actually sort of hijack that sense
实际上会劫持你的身份
of identity it can really steal a person
认同感，让你迷失
away from themselves and we I think it's
自我。我认为这
so important because we haven't given
非常重要，因为我们作为一个
culture as a field of mental health to
社会，作为一个心理健康领域，一直没有
identify this as a problem and allow
意识到这是一个问题，也没有允许
people to have responses in a way it's
人们做出相应的回应。在某种程度上，
nice to say the narcissistic people are
说自恋型人格的人
not very nice it's a strange Paradox in
不友善似乎被认为是一种不友好的说法。这在心理健康领域是一个奇怪的悖论。
the world of mental health that's why I
这就是我
do it because nothing more than me
做这件事的原因，因为我
wanting to return people back to their
只想帮助人们回归
authentic s you must have seen the cost
真实的自我。你一定见过
of narcissism can you give me some
自恋的代价，你能举一些
has had on someone's life that you've
你见过的自恋者对他人生活造成的影响的例子吗？
seen oh where do I begin I'll tell you
哦，我该从何说起呢？我告诉你，
cost is a person person who so doesn't
代价就是一个人极度缺乏自信，甚至
believe in themselves that they may give
可能
up on their path of education and never
放弃学业，永远无法实现目标。
pursue an interest so we never got to
追求兴趣，所以我们从未有机会
see the work product that that would
看到他们
have created not to mention that person
最终的作品，更不用说他们有机会真正
actually getting to unfurl their wings
展翅高飞，成为
and fully be who they wanted to be as a
他们想成为的
creative or as a professional it's the
创意人士或专业人士了。这个
person who knew what they wanted to be
人原本知道自己想要什么，
that they had a very strong identity as
拥有非常强烈的自我认同感，却
pick something and they ended up
最终
choosing something else because they
选择了别的，因为他们
knew the only way they could be loved
知道，只有
was to be what that parent demanded of
满足父母的要求，才能获得爱。他们
them and it was so clear to them they
很清楚，
wouldn't be loved unless they fully gave
除非完全顺从父母的期望，否则就得不到爱。这个人原本
it's the person who was an absolutely
是一个无比
glorious human being lovely empathic and
美好的人，可爱、富有同情心、
warm but feel so damaged after years of
热情，但多年来不断被
being told you're not enough you're
告知“你不够好”、“你
selfish you're greedy you're foolish
自私”、“你贪婪”、“你愚蠢”，内心深受创伤，以至于
that they get into relationship after
他们一次又一次地陷入重复
relationship that duplic LIC Ates that
这种
theme and don't get the real
主题的感情关系，却得不到他们应得的真正充满
collaborative compassionate love story
合作与关怀的爱情故事，
that they deserve because they don't
因为他们
think they deserve it and that's just
觉得自己不配拥有。而这仅仅是
the top of the iceberg and your academic
冰山一角。你的学术
background your the experience that
背景，你的经验，这些
experience so my my experience is in in
经验又是什么呢？我的经验是……
my academic background is I have a PhD
我的学术背景是
in Clinical Psychology and my minor is
临床心理学博士，
in something called Health psychology
辅修健康心理学。
and so I got really interested in how
因此，我对
various elements of mental health and
心理健康和
mental illness showed up in people who
精神疾病的各种因素如何在同时患有其他疾病的人群中表现出来非常感兴趣。这或许是
it's a very almost like Strange point to
一个比较特殊的切入点，
enter but what we do know is people
但我们确实知道，
personality affects how we take care of
人格会影响我们如何照顾
our health how we might engage in
自己的健康，以及我们可能会做出哪些危害
behaviors that might put our health at
健康的行为。
risk for example narcissism and
例如，自恋和
addiction have a really high overlap so
成瘾之间存在很高的重叠度。
here's a case of now a personality Style
这里举个例子，某种人格类型会
putting a person at health risk due to
因为使用药物来调节情绪而使人处于健康风险之中，并由此引发一系列问题。
but it's tough to measure personality
但是，斯蒂芬，人格很难衡量，真的很难
measure it's not one of those things
衡量。
it's not like a blood test it's not even
它不像验血那样简单，甚至不像
like measuring depression frankly
测量抑郁症那样容易。坦白说，
depression is eminently measurable yeah
抑郁症是可以测量的，虽然它有
there's different variants and there's
不同的类型和
different severity but we're very clear
不同的严重程度，但我们在
diagnostically and phenomenologically
诊断和现象学上非常清楚
what makes depression what qualifies
抑郁症的成因。而
personality is like the wild west and so
人格的定义则像狂野西部一样难以捉摸。因此，
from a research perspective it's
从研究的角度来看，
something that people would often shy
人们常常会
away from because we couldn't get the
回避这个问题，因为我们无法
constructs right but I said I welcome
准确地构建人格模型。但我表示欢迎
the challenge because I truly in my
挑战，因为我真心
heart believe
相信，
if we could understand and study
如果我们能够更深入地理解和研究
personality more we'd actually be
人格，我们就能真正
understanding all this unmeasurable
理解
noise in the mental health research
心理健康研究中那些难以量化的噪音。
because I thought that's probably where
我认为问题可能就出在这里，
it was and I think more and more of the
而且越来越多的
research is supporting that and you
研究也支持这一观点。
spend time even today dealing with
即使在今天，你仍然会花时间与那些身陷
narcissistic relationship or the victim
自恋关系或被
of a narcissist every week every week I
自恋者伤害的患者打交道，每周都是如此。这
mean it's it's probably one of the if
或许是我每周最有
not the most gratifying part of my my
成就感的工作之一，甚至可以说是最有成就感的工作。
week I'm a big believer that if you're a
我坚信，如果你是一名
mental health practitioner you practice
心理健康从业者，你就应该专注于
mental health so that's a privilege to
心理健康，能够置身于
be able to be in that room and to work
咨询室，与
with clients but it would be so easy
患者一起工作是一种荣幸。但是，
when you're dealing at a macro level
当你在宏观层面研究
large populations going on YouTube
庞大的人群，比如在YouTube上发布视频、
writing books to get distanced from what
撰写书籍时，很容易就会与个体的
lives one of the tricky bits with
生活脱节。研究的难点之一在于，
research is we study populations we
我们研究的是群体，我们
study samples right we study hundreds of
研究的是样本，我们研究的是成百上千的
people what happens in the room is
人。 房间里发生的
something very different and you start
事情截然不同，你会开始
to recognize a how badly these
意识到：首先，这些
relationships harm people their schemas
关系对人们的伤害有多大，包括他们
of the world their schemas of themselves
对世界的认知
and B how much potential for
和自我认知；其次，
through very very simple approaches
通过一些非常简单的方法，比如
around education about narcissism
教育他们关于自恋的认知、
validation of their experience breaking
认可他们的经历、帮助他们打破
through self-blame and teaching them to
自责并教会他们
trust themselves so how many patients do
信任自己，就能对这些来访者进行多大的干预。所以，
you think you've seen that have been
你觉得你见过多少
victims of narcissists I mean hundreds
自恋者的受害者？我的意思是，成百上千，真的
hundreds really and I even use the word
成百上千。我甚至用“
Survivor I hate to call them victims
幸存者”这个词，我讨厌称他们为受害者，
because I don't even think they're that
因为我不认为他们那么
passive I mean I think that they just
被动。我的意思是，我认为他们只是……从来
weren't no one ever taught anyone this
没有人教过他们这些。
right I give you the example when people
我举个例子，当人们和有
who's living with addiction it's very
成瘾问题的人谈恋爱时，
clear what they're dealing with right
他们面临的情况非常清楚。这个
you have a person they're using a
人正在使用某种物质，这种物质
substance that's altering them that's
改变了他们，
altering their behavior that's taking
改变了他们的行为，让他们失去了自我。
people in relationships with addicts
和瘾君子谈恋爱的人
will say I'm in two relationships I'm in
会说：“我同时维持着两段关系，一段是
a relationship with a sober person and
和清醒的人谈恋爱，另一段是
I'm in a relationship with somebody
和……谈恋爱。”
who's using or intoxicated or denying or
谁在吸毒、酗酒、否认或为
defending their use right two people and
自己的行为辩护，这都会破坏两个人的关系。
relationships and we're willing to call
我们愿意称之为“关系破裂”。
it that the experience people have in
人们在自恋型人格障碍患者
narcissistic relationships in a way is
关系中的经历，在某种程度上与吸毒
no different with the added bit though
并无二致，只是多了一点：
that at least with addiction people can
至少对于成瘾，人们会
say I see what the behavior is I see
说“我明白这种行为是什么，我明白
what the issue is addiction's a disease
问题所在。成瘾是一种疾病，
and we know it's treatable narcissism
我们知道它是可以治疗的。”而
narcissistic person has this very
自恋型人格障碍则不然。此外，自恋者拥有一套非常
well-developed very successful
完善且成功的
behavioral repertoire they can go out in
社交技巧，他们可以在外人面前展现
charming and charismatic and confident
魅力、自信、
and smart and the center of attention
聪明，成为众人瞩目的焦点，甚至
and running companies and behind closed
经营公司。但在
doors they psychologically eviscerate
私下里，他们会在心理上摧毁与自己相处的
the people they're with spouses Partners
人——配偶、伴侣、
family members close friends maybe
家人、密友，甚至是
organization people where they can kind
组织中地位低于自己的人——总之，他们会在那些可以
of get away with it so the people
逍遥法外的地方伤害他人。因此，那些被他们
they're harming the world thinks this
伤害的人，至少会觉得这个
person's fantastic at least a person
人很棒。与
who's in a relationship with an addict
瘾君子交往的人会
people say okay get it they're using
说：“好吧，明白了，他们在吸毒。”
this is hard but for the folks in
很难，但对于那些身处
narcissistic relationships a lot of
自恋关系中的人来说，很多
people say aren't you lucky that you're
人会说“你真幸运
married to that guy and the person's
嫁给了那样的人”，而当事人则会想“
like oh my gosh are these people out
天哪，这些人到底是怎么想的？”。
there mind like so what do they do they
那么他们会怎么做呢？他们会
blame
责怪
themselves
自己。
okay what is
好吧，什么是
narcissism because I've heard the word
自恋？因为我经常听到这个词，
used so often but I couldn't tell you
但我却说不出
the definition of it and I feel like I'd
它的定义，而且我觉得如果我说错了，肯定会歪曲它的意思。
so I'm almost curious to ask you yeah
所以我很好奇地想问问你，在
what just before I almost contaminate
我把我的定义“污染”到你之前，
what's your working definition what's
你对自恋的定义是什么？你对自恋的理解是什么？
arrogance um and they're cruel okay all
嗯，妄自尊大，认为自己非常重要，比所有人都强，傲慢，而且残忍。好吧，
like a C+ B minus if you're student in
如果你是我的学生，我可能会给你C+到B-的分数。我的
my class I mean I I I cut students a lot
意思是，我以前对学生很
of slack back in day so I'll give you C+
宽容，所以我会给你C+到
B minus because you're in the
B-，因为你…… 邻里关系，自大、
arrogance the the meanness but that to
傲慢、刻薄，但对
me is even more sort of a manifestation
我来说，这更像是
of the traits like the grandiosity the
自大和
arrogance they have variable empathy and
傲慢等特质的一种表现。他们的同理心时好时坏，
typically have low empathy they're
通常很低。他们
deeply entitled they truly think they're
极度自负，真的认为自己
more special than everyone else and that
比任何人都特殊，
the rules should apply to them very
规则应该对他们完全适用。
differently they have a excessive need
他们过度需要
for admiration and validation they're
赞美和认可，
very superficial they don't really have
非常肤浅，没有
the capacity for deep sustained Intimate
能力建立深厚持久的亲密
Relationships they're very much
关系。他们非常
referential to the world out there out
依赖
outside of them to set goals they don't
外部世界来设定目标，没有清晰的
have an good internal sense of like what
内在认知，不知道什么
matters to me what what do I want to do
对我来说重要，我想做什么。
they just want to do what they do again
他们只想重复自己一直在做的事情，
to get that admiration and validation
以获得赞美和认可。
shallowness to narcissism those are the
自恋中有一种肤浅，一种真正的情感肤浅。这些是
patterns and traits we sort of see
我们看到的模式和特征。
they're very very self-centered very
他们非常非常以自我为中心，非常
preoccupied with themselves the good
关注自己，关注自己好的
parts of themselves the bad parts of
一面和坏的一面。
themselves it's very rare for them to
他们很少会
sort of lift their heads up and
抬起头来，
genuinely notice the experience of
真正地…… 注意观察他人的经历，
another person that's what narcissism is
这就是自恋的本质。
how does it show up it shows up as
它表现为
devaluation dismissiveness manipulation
贬低、漠视、操控和
gaslighting they get angry very quickly
煤气灯效应。他们很容易生气，
especially when they're frustrated or
尤其是在沮丧或
disappointed and that can show up as
失望的时候，这种愤怒可能表现为
overt Rage or overt anger yelling
公开的暴怒、
screaming or even violence that can show
大喊大叫，甚至暴力。也可能
up as passive aggression with holding
表现为被动攻击，例如冷漠
and withdrawing they are they can be
和退缩。他们容易背叛，撒谎、
cheat they make promises about the
欺骗，对未来做出承诺却
future they never keep but they do that
从不兑现，但他们这样做是
to keep people around so they won't
为了留住身边的人，防止他们
leave them so it's it's part of a larger
离开。这是一种更大规模的
sort of a manipulation they will
操控手段。他们会
dominate people they have to get the
控制他人，必须争个输赢，会把责任推卸
last word they will shift blame onto
给
other people they will rarely take
别人。他们很少
responsibility for their misdeeds even
为自己的过错承担责任，即使被
when they're clearly caught in them and
抓包，也会把责任
if they do they'll still blame the other
推卸给
person they're very neglectful and
别人。他们对人际关系非常疏忽和
careless and relationships that is
粗心，这就是
narcissism how can you tell the
自恋。如何区分心情
difference between someone having a bad
不好的人、
day an [__] and a narcissist because
混蛋和自恋者呢？因为
some of those things there I thought on
有些…… 我觉得，如果心情
a bad day I might do that yeah you know
不好，我可能会那样做。你知道，嗯，把
um the whole collection together no but
所有事情都放在一起。不，但如果心情不好，没睡好，
you know what I might blame someone or
我可能会责怪别人或
whatever else what's the distinction
其他什么。
when a person has a bad day and we all
当一个人心情不好时，我们都会经历心情不好的时候，有什么区别呢？
have bad days and on those bad days we
在那些糟糕的日子里，我们
might look if all the if the only tape
可能会想，如果别人唯一记录下
someone had of us was of that day right
我们的录像就是那天拍的，对吧？
but the here's the piece when people are
但关键在于，当人们
not narcissistic and they have bad days
不自恋，即使心情不好，
they will take accountability they will
他们也会承担责任，会
make amends and they will change their
弥补过错，会改变自己的
behavior and say I'm not doing this
行为，会说“我不会再这样做了，这样做不对，
again this is this is not okay why
为什么不对？”
wasn't it okay because it was none of
因为这不是任何
those people's fault you didn't get
人的错，你没睡好。
enough sleep and whether that means we
这意味着我们要更
reach deeper to be as kind as we can to
深入地去理解
the people in some cases especially if
他人，尽可能地善待他们。在某些情况下，尤其是当我们遇到
it's people we know or we see you may
认识的人或同事时，你可能
not know the random person at the gym
不认识健身房里的陌生人，
but if we someone we know or work with
但如果是我们认识的人或同事，
we step we step out of ourselves to say
我们会走出自己的舒适区，说“
the way I conducted myself yesterday
我昨天的行为
wasn't okay and I'm really sorry about
不对，我真的很抱歉”。
that um and so that that they're having
这样他们就能体验到
that experience of you taking
你承担
accountability that's where I know we're
责任的感觉，我知道我们
not dealing with a narcissistic person
面对的不是一个自恋的人，
we're dealing with a bad day and a bad
而只是糟糕的一天。糟糕的一天就是糟糕的
day is just that a day it's not every
一天，并非
day with a narcissistic person many days
自恋的人每天都如此。很多时候——
I'm not going to say all but many days
我不是说所有时候——但很多时候都
are characterized by these machinations
充斥着各种阴谋诡计、
these manipulations and these
操控和
invalidations the person in a
否定。
relationship with a narcissistic person
与自恋者相处的人会
feel like they're constantly on their
感觉自己总是处于
back foot that they can't be themselves
被动，无法做自己，无法表达
they can't express a need they can't
需求，无法
express a want they can't even express a
表达愿望，甚至无法表达
feeling for fear of it being shut down
感受，因为害怕被否定。
so there's your so there's your not
所以，这就是你所说的非
narcissistic person what about an
自恋的人。那么，混蛋呢？
[__] okay I do think assholery and
好吧，我认为混蛋和
narcissism are pretty they we use the
自恋很相似，我们经常互换使用这两个
terms
词。
interchangeably I think though that
不过，我认为，关于混蛋的
here's here's my [__] belief since
看法是，由于
this is something it's I think the
这是一个概念，我认为
construct validation on [__] is
对混蛋的建构验证
probably still needing to be done I
可能仍然需要进行。我
think [__] tend to be pretty
认为混蛋…… 他们往往一直都很
consistently [__] so whereas
混蛋，而
narcissistic people can really they have
自恋的人则不然，他们拥有
a much wider behavioral repertoire to be
更广泛的行为模式，可以表现得
absolutely Charming this is a person who
魅力十足。比如，一个人
can be absolutely Charming on the golf
可以在高尔夫球
course with the CEO of their company
场上和公司CEO打得非常迷人，热情友好，还
like Charming nice warm remember during
记得
the ages of their kids and asking about
孩子在哪的时候，会问起
the wife and remembering that their
妻子，记得
grandmother is sick and all this stuff
奶奶生病等等。然后
and get home forget it was his
回到家，却忘了那天是他们的
anniversary scream at their partner why
结婚纪念日，冲着伴侣大吼：“为什么
is the house like look like this why do
家里这么乱？
I have to put up with this make those
我为什么要忍受这一切？让那些
damn kids shut up but they were Mr I
该死的孩子闭嘴！” 但在高尔夫球场上，他们却会说：“我
remember that your little girl's
记得你女儿的
birthday is February 6th when they were
生日是2月6日。”
on the golf course that is not assholery
这不是混蛋行为，
that's narcissism can you cure
这是自恋。你认为自恋可以治愈吗？
because I think that would imply
我认为不能，因为那意味着
changing a personality which I don't
改变一个人的性格，而我
think we can
认为我们做不到。
seen in your 20 years of working with
在你与
narcissists and their
自恋者及其
survivors any sign of a narcissist
受害者共事的20年里，你有没有见过任何自恋者
becoming a not- narcissist or non-
变成非自恋者的迹象？
narcissist I've not seen them become a
我没见过非自恋者变成
not- narcissist I've be seen them make
非自恋者，但我见过他们做出一些
micro changes because I measure and
细微的改变。因为我
monitor and make my notes in therapy so
在治疗过程中会进行评估、观察和记录，所以
I'll see interesting they're no longer
我会发现一些有趣的事情：他们不再
trying to mess with coming in 10 minutes
试图拖延，比如迟到十分钟
later and asking me to keep them for the
后才来，然后要求我留他们一
whole hour they are honoring the
整小时；他们尊重
therapeutic frame they're paying the
治疗的框架；
bill when they decide not to show up at
如果他们临时决定不来，他们会按时支付费用。
the last minute I see Tiny tweaks I'll
我看到的是一些细微的调整。我
see people who'll come in and
见过有人进来跟我
say I screamed at my girlfriend again
说：“我昨晚又对女朋友大吼大叫了，
last night and that wasn't cool so I was
这太不好了。”我当时想：“
like oh who that's Insight like I'll run
哦，这算什么？这算是洞察力吧。”我会顺着这个思路继续下去。
with it but here's the rub okay these
但问题在于，这些
micro changes and they are micro changes
细微的改变——它们确实是改变——虽然只是微小的改变，
but they are changes and they're in the
但它们是改变，而且是朝着
right
正确的
direction that much water under under
方向发展。
the bridge for the family members and
对于那些受到伤害的家人、
partners and other people that have been
伴侣和其他人来说，很多事情已经过去了。
harmed they're saying you want me to
他们会说：“你想让我继续维持
stay in this relationship because this
这段关系，就因为这个
dude remember to say thank you once this
人这周记得说一次谢谢。”
week I think not to me the thank you is
我觉得这不算什么。对我来说，一句“谢谢”对
progress to the people in their lives
他们生活中受到伤害的人来说就是一种进步。
who've been harmed that one thank you is
一句“谢谢”远远
not going to be
不够。
enough when I was looking at the subject
当我研究
of narcissism and I was looking at what
自恋这个话题，并查看
people are searching around the subject
人们围绕这个主题的搜索内容时，
matter I could see no searches online
我发现网上几乎没有人搜索“我的
for is my my wife a narcissist but I saw
妻子是自恋者吗？”，但却有
lots of searches for is my husband a
很多人搜索“我的丈夫是
narcissist really yes so I
自恋者吗？”。没错，所以我
wondered is narcissism a gender specific
很想知道自恋是否与性别有关，
thing and in What proportion do you
以及
typically see men and women being
男性和女性
narcissists yeah no it's not gender
自恋者的比例通常是多少。是的，不，它与性别无关。
specific I'm so shocked at that because
我对此感到非常震惊，因为
I've worked with so many men who have
我接触过很多男性，他们的
narcissistic wives or female partners
妻子或伴侣都是自恋者；
and I've worked with many I've worked
我也接触过
with many lesbian couples I've I mean
很多女同性恋伴侣，
I've worked with cases where clearly it
我甚至接触过一些案例，其中很明显
was a woman female identified person who
是女性自恋者。
is narcissistic it is definitely not
自恋绝对不
limited to men so here's what we know
局限于男性。我们知道，
grandiose narcissism much more common in
夸大性自恋在男性中更为常见，
men malignant narcissism much more
恶性自恋
common in men but there's a form of
在男性中也更为常见，但还有一种…… 有一种
narcissism called vulnerable
自恋被称为脆弱型自恋。
narcissism vulnerable narcissism isn't
脆弱型自恋并非那种
so much of the showy charismatic
张扬、魅力四射、爱出风头、傲慢自大、爱推销、
attention seeking narcissist the
寻求关注的自恋者。
vulnerable narcissist is more socially
脆弱型自恋者往往更易感到社交
anxious victimized Sullen resentful
焦虑、受害、阴郁、怨恨和
grieved and often we sort of see a
悲伤。我们经常会看到他们缺乏主动权，会抱怨“
I'm angry at the world how come I never
我恨这个世界，为什么我总是
got my turn you know makes how come she
错过机会？”、“为什么她
got that and you know I I was better
得到了那个？”、“我比
than him I should have gotten that
他强，我本该得到那个。”
balanced okay so these other types of
等等。这是一种受害者心态，没错，这就是所谓的脆弱型自恋。当我们审视脆弱型自恋时，性别比例要平衡。
narcissism you named four types there
你提到的其他几种自恋类型，比如
grandiose narcissism right so that's our
夸大型自恋，就是我们
traditional sort of garden variety
通常所说的那种常见的自恋，
narcissism the showy charismatic
张扬、魅力四射、自命不凡、
pretentious preing Charming attention
爱出风头、
seeking actually quite often quite
寻求关注。事实上，这类自恋
successful narcissistic person unlike
者往往相当成功，这与脆弱型自恋者截然不同。
the vulnerable narcissists who are
那些“
Failure to Launch the grandiose
无法成功”的
narcissistic people often have big big
自恋型人格障碍者，往往怀揣着远大的
dreams and they'll execute not always
梦想，他们也会努力实现这些梦想，但并非总是如此。他们
not always and they'll often burn
常常会
Bridges because they are in fact
因为
narcissistic so they'll anger people or
自恋而断送人际关系，所以他们会惹恼别人、
do Shady deals or cut people out and all
进行不正当的交易​​、疏远他人等等。
that stuff but the grandio narcissistic
但自恋型人格障碍者
folks are often the Larger than Life
往往是那种“超凡脱俗”的人。
folks now if they are angry at you if
如果
they feel let down by you they will let
他们对你生气，或者感到失望，他们会让
you know they can be very vindictive
你知道。他们可能非常记仇，
they are not going to be very honest in
在人际关系中不会很诚实，他们很可能会
betray you they're going to be mean to
背叛你，他们也会对
their Partners we can count on that too
伴侣很刻薄，这一点我们也可以预料到。
but to the World At Large Larger than
但在世人眼中，他们总是“超凡脱俗”。这就是
Life That's the typical model now the
典型的自恋型人格障碍模式。而
vulnerable narcissism is what I narc IST
我刚才提到的脆弱型自恋，就是我所说的“脆弱型自恋”，它
is what I just shared with you that more
更
vulnerable victimized sorry victimized
脆弱、更易受伤害、更易受伤害、更易
socially anxious angry AG grieved Sullen
社交焦虑、更易愤怒、更易悲伤、更阴郁、更易怨恨的“无法成功”自恋者。
okay some people would argue they're one
好吧，有些人可能会对此提出异议。 他们本质上是一回事，
and the same that as long as a grandiose
只要
narcissistic person is well supplied
自恋型人格的人生活富足，
things are going well they're getting
一切顺利，备受
lots of attention they're making money
关注，赚得盆满钵满，
they're they're just sort of feeling
感觉自己无所不能，他们就会一直
to stay in their grandiose mode however
保持自恋的状态。然而，
if the thing tips
一旦情况发生变化，
grandiose narcissist they lose the money
自恋型人格的人失去金钱、
they lose the job they lose the partner
失去工作、失去伴侣、
they lose social status the vulnerable
失去社会地位，他们脆弱的一面就会
stuff will start showing up the
开始显现：
victimhood the resentment this is a
受害者心态、怨恨、“亲爱的，你被
witch hon everyone's out to get me can
女巫盯上了，每个人都想害我”之类的想法，甚至会
almost feel sort of lowgrade paranoid
感到轻微的妄想。你更偏向于其中一种类型。
the vulnerable narcissist could
脆弱型自恋者
definitely have a grandiose moment if
如果
everything turned for them but some
一切顺利，也可能会表现出自恋的一面，但有些
people are just more grandiose some
人天生就更自恋，有些
people are more vulnerable but they do
人则更脆弱，但他们
have the other underbelly that's just
都有不为人知的另一面。这就是自恋型人格的写照。至于
that's how that looks now the malignant
恶性
narcissist which is another type I
自恋者，也就是我之前提到的另一种类型，
talked about this is where we see the
我们在这里看到的是……
most severe form and when I say most
最严重的自恋形式，我所说的最
severe most severe in terms of how it
严重是指它
shows up in relationships I'd say the
在人际关系中的表现，我认为它是
most problematic form of narcissism and
最棘手的自恋形式。这种
here's where we see a form of narcissism
自恋
that shows up as manipulativeness
表现为操控、剥削、利用
advantage of people um coerciveness I
他人、胁迫、
isolation using Menace as a tool of
孤立、以威胁作为
control very vindictive dangerous it
控制手段、报复心强、危险，甚至
could be quite dangerous um this this is
可能非常危险。
I always say malignant narcissism is the
我总是说，恶性自恋是到达
psychopathy station because this is as
精神病态车站前的最后一站，因为它与
close to psychopathy as you're going to
精神病态非常接近，但又不是
get without it being psychopathy and in
精神病态。
fact there's a personality model called
事实上，有一种人格模型叫做“
the dark tetrad and the dark tetrad is
黑暗四元组”，它由
comprised of narcissism psychopathy
自恋、精神病态、
machiavellianism which is sort of like
马基雅维利主义（类似于
that willingness to use other people for
利用他人为
your own advantage and sadism I
自己谋利）和虐待狂组成。我
personally think there should be a fifth
个人认为应该加上第五个
bit which is par oia because I think
维度，即“偏执”，因为我认为
these folks can be really think
这些人真的会觉得
everyone's out to get them but the model
每个人都想害他们。但
right now is those four pieces right
目前的模型是这样的：
malignant narcissism has a lot of those
恶性自恋的四个特征中，有很多都属于此类：精心
top notes the calculated callous
策划的
coldness the shallow charm the shallow
冷酷无情、肤浅的魅力、
lack of empathy the in some ways getting
缺乏同理心，以及在某种程度上从
some pleasure out of seeing someone who
看到伤害过自己的人
wronged them being hurt so again it
受到伤害中获得快感。因此，恶性
malignant narcissism is that your say
自恋感觉更加危险。这就是恶性自恋。你说
serial killers I would say the serial
连环杀手就是这样吗？我认为连环
killers are probably more Psychopathic
杀手可能更像精神病患者，
and psychopathy is definitely a
而精神病绝对是另一种
different subtype it's different
亚型，它与
malignant narcissism they're not the
恶性自恋截然不同。精神病患者和恶性自恋不是
same thing they they they they look
一回事，它们看起来不一样，
different even genetically and all and
甚至在基因上也不同，
different in the brain Psychopathic
大脑结构可能也不同。精神病
people have um they don't have remorse
患者没​​有悔恨，
they don't feel guilt whereas malignant
没有内疚感，而恶性
narcissistic people may they know they
自恋者可能知道自己
did something wrong a psychopathic
做错了事，但精神病
person it's almost as though they don't
患者似乎根本不
understand what they did wrong not
明白自己错在哪里，不是
because they have a mental deficit but
因为他们有智力缺陷，而是
because they literally have zero
因为他们完全没有同理心。
capacity for empathy and the fourth type
第四种类型
of narcissism so I gave you vulnerable
我之前提到了自恋的几种类型：脆弱型、
grandiose malignant and the fourth type
夸大型、恶性型，第四种
is communal narcissism right grandios
是群体自恋，对吧？夸大型、
malignant vulnerable yes the fourth type
恶性型、脆弱型，没错，第四种
is communal narcissism communal
是群体自恋。群体
narcissism is very interesting it's a
自恋很有意思，它是这个
relatively new construct in the field it
领域一个相对较新的概念，大约在
came around 2003 was when I started
2003年出现。那时我开始
reading some of the first papers by a
读一些
guy Nam Gau I think he was writing he
Nam Gau的论文，我记得他当时在
was the University of munic the time and
慕尼黑大学工作。
I I loved the work I thought it was
我很喜欢他的研究，觉得它
absolutely compelling because it was
非常有说服力，因为它提出了这样一个
this idea that there were people out
观点：有些人
there who were going to get their
获取
narcissistic Supply not through the
自恋供给的方式并非像
usual look at me I'm so great I'm going
通常那样——“看我多棒！我要
to do things so people tell me I'm great
做什么事，让别人夸我！”——
but by doing good deeds by being
而是通过做好事，被
perceived as saviors by being perceived
视为救世主，被视为
as Grand Rescuers humanitarians so the
伟大的拯救者、人道主义者。所以，
communal narcissist is a person who gets
群体自恋者就是通过做好事来获得
their narcissistic Supply their praise
自恋供给——赞扬、
their admiration their Awe by doing
钦佩和敬畏——的人。 做好
motivation for doing the good deeds not
事的动机并非出于做好
the good deed in and of itself not
事本身，而是出于想要被视为好人的目的。
because you care about a refugee group
你做事并非出于对难民群体的关心，也
not because you care about the plight of
并非出于对动物困境的关注，
animals but because you want to be
而是因为你想被
viewed as a good dude and so that's the
视为好人。这就是
communal narcissist now what gets
群体性自恋者。
interesting like with all forms of
有趣的是，所有形式的
narcissism all narcissism is on a
自恋都处于一个
spectrum it's not an either or from mild
连续谱上，并非非此即彼，而是从轻微
to severe all of mental health is on a
到严重。心理健康也处于一个
spectrum there's no such thing as a
连续谱上，不存在非
black and white dichotomy and mental
黑即白的二元对立。心理
health it's it's it's mild to severe
健康也是从轻微到严重，从
mild to severe and what's interesting
轻微到严重。
with communal narcissism at the lowest
群体性自恋者最有趣的地方在于，在最
ends it's sort of like you're more like
低端，他们更像是
Instagram saviors like look at me I'm
Instagram上的救世主，仿佛在说“看我，我在
saving the world but you know like
拯救世界”。但你知道，
they're cleaning up the beach in their
他们穿着比基尼清理海滩，
bikini and I'm like is this about how
我就想问，这到底是为了炫耀
attractive you are is this about really
你的魅力，还是真的在
trying to save the environment like it
努力保护环境？
really is about are we talking about
我们到底是在讨论
apps or are we talking about trash in
应用程序，还是真的在做环保？ 他们会谈论
the street like what are we talking
街上的垃圾，好像在说些什么似的，
about but they want the validation like
但他们却渴望得到认可，比如“
what a cool person you are for spending
你周末去救大象真是个很酷的人”。大象其实相对
relatively harmless they're moderately
无害，它们的行为也有些
ridiculous but they do get angry if
荒谬，但如果
people don't give them a big Bravo for
人们不为它们的
how humanitarian they are you take
人道主义精神喝彩，它们就会生气。如果你把
communal narcissism all the way to the
群体性自恋推向
severe end of the spectrum you're
极端，你就会发现
talking about a cult leader these are
邪教头目。这些
now people who are saying I have the
人会说“我掌握了
answer to the universe I know everything
宇宙的答案，我无所不知，我比你更了解你”。
I know you better than you they'll bring
他们会把
people into cultic systems they will
人拉进邪教体系，
completely you know separate them from
彻底剥夺他们的
their sense of self and their sense of
自我意识和
self-worth have no problem doing it it
自我价值感，毫不费力地做到这一点，并一直
and tell them that they're doing them a
告诉他们这样做是
good thing the whole time that's to me
好事。在我看来，这就是
your your severe cult leader or I think
极端邪教头目，或者说
all cult leader cult leader forget
所有邪教头目——别说极端
where communal and malignant narcissism
邪教头目了——群体性自恋和恶性自恋的结合点很可能就是邪教头目。
come together the big question how many
一个重要的问题是：有多少
people are narcissists this is a big
人是自恋者？这是一个大
question because our problem is this
问题，因为我们面临的问题是，目前还
there's really no good studies about
没有关于这方面的可靠研究。
this it's tough to measure narcissism
很难衡量自恋，谁会
who's really going to cop to being
承认自己
really entitled or really manipulative
非常自以为是或非常善于操纵别人呢？
you often don't get people who are going
你通常很难找到愿意
to answer those questions in an honest
坦诚回答这些问题的人。
open way when we look at the prevalence
当我们研究大规模流行病学研究中
of narcissistic personality disorder
自恋型人格障碍的患病率时，
scale epidemiologic studies we see the
我们发现
rates to be somewhere between 1 and 6%
患病率在1%到6%之间，
but that's the diagnosis and that's in
但这只是诊断结果，而且是在
really structured research settings
非常结构化的研究环境下得出的。
narcissism is a person who has enough of
自恋是指一个人具有足够明显的
the narcissistic personality style to be
自恋型人格特征，以至于
noticeable to be experienced by others
他人能够感受到。
it's a spitball number because we've
这只是一个大概的数字，因为我们
never done the numbers so I'd say if the
从未进行过实际统计。所以我认为，如果这个
spitball number is probably sit in
数字是
somewhere between 15 and 18% I think
15%到18%，
that's a good guess about one in six
那应该比较合理，大约六分之一的
people I think if you're in a major
人患有自恋型人格障碍。我认为，如果你生活在
metropolitan area it's going to be a
大都市地区，这个比例会
little higher I think in certain
更高一些；在某些
industries it's going to be higher um I
行业，
think in certain maybe even cultures it
甚至在某些文化中，这个比例
could be higher so but if you were going
也会更高。 所以，如果你要
to just give me ask me for a global
问我全球
prevalence I mean I think that's it's my
患病率，我的意思是，我认为这是
it's my best guess and I think a lot of
我的最佳猜测，而且我认为很多
folks in the field might agree with me
业内人士可能也会同意我的看法。患病率高到足以引起
again enough of it that you'd notice it
注意，
enough of it that people are being
足以
affected by it so you've met six team
影响人们的生活。你见过我的六位团队
members of mine including me I have not
成员，包括我，但
I've only met four of you so you're
我只见过你们四位，所以
still two men down you're okay you might
你们还差两位。没关系，你们可能还在努力，
still be coming it through cuz my next
因为我的下一个
question was which one do you think it
问题是，你认为到目前为止，哪个群体
was so far so bad for you because each
对你来说最糟糕？因为
one of us has been sweeter than the next
我们每个人的情况都比下一个更糟。
so Stephen you're in the hot seat right
所以，斯蒂芬，你
now oh gosh sugar okay interesting okay
现在可要倒霉了。哦，天哪，糖。好吧，有意思。好吧，我的
so I mean one and six as a as a spitball
意思是，1/6，作为一个粗略估计的
number is is scarily high that's
数字，这个数字高得吓人。这很
interesting you think it's scarily High
有意思，你觉得它高得吓人？我的
I mean I I think it's
意思是，我认为大约是……
about I mean listen we know how I I I
听着，我们知道……我
actually don't think it is I think if
其实不这么认为。我认为如果
you went to a small town you might hit
你去一个小镇，你可能会遇到
closer to one in eight because I think a
接近八分之一的情况，因为我认为
small town is almost based on a greater
小镇几乎都是基于……
need for sociality I think there's more
我认为，人们对社交的需求越来越大，
interdependence in that kind of a
在这种情况下，相互依赖性也更强，
situation so narcissism isn't going to
所以自恋可能不太
probably work as well but I I mean one
适用。我的意思是，
in six I think if any of us really went
如果我们每个人真的
home and did the soul searching listed
回家认真反思，列出所有
out the names of everyone we knew the
认识的人的名字，这个
number is probably going to track is
数字可能会
that number increasing are we breeding
上升。我们是否
narcissists because of the sort of
因为社会变迁而滋生了自恋者？说到
occurred I'm thinking about Instagram
Instagram，我就在想，
is is social media a narcissist Creator
社交媒体是自恋的制造者吗？
it's I think it's a it's a narcissist
我认为它是一个自恋的
amplifier but I don't think it's a
放大器，但我不认为它是制造者。
Creator narcissism is a personality
自恋是一种人格
style and like all personality Styles
类型，就像所有人格类型一样，
it's a social emotional developmental
它是一种
phenomenon that happens from infancy
从婴儿期
into adolescence so somebody jumping
到青春期的社会情感发展现象。所以，如果有人
onto Instagram when they're 18 and
18岁才开始玩Instagram，
posted lots of selfies they're a decent
发了很多自拍，他们仍然是个不错的
person that's not going to turn them
人，这不会让他们变成
narcissistic it might turn them boring
自恋者，可能会让他们变得无趣，
but I don't know that it would
但我不知道这是否
necessarily turn them narcissistic I
一定会让他们变成自恋者。 我
think it could take if somebody's got
觉得自恋可能指的是，如果一个人具备某些
the traits they have the tendency to
特质，他们就倾向于
need the validation and admiration and
需要别人的认可和赞美。但是，
again a person posting selfies that
一个人发自拍
doesn't make them narcissistic because
并不代表他就是自恋的，因为
Jack went on holiday up this mountain
杰克去山上度假，
and he posted loads of photos Okay so no
他发了很多照片。好吧，
but but we have to if Jack's a nice
但是，我们必须假设杰克是个
person right jack is excited to share
好人，对吧？杰克很兴奋地想
his trip with everyone right but he was
和大家分享他的旅行，对吧？但他有点炫耀，
kind of like rubbing it in okay so it's
好吧，没错，
a that's right Jack just lost some
杰克因此丢了一些
points there poor Jack but it's a but
分，可怜的杰克。
but I would say this what what we' want
但是，我想说的是，我们想
to know with anyone who's posted a lot
知道的是，对于那些经常发
of vacation photos right and they keep
度假照片的人，
doing it how present are they when
当他们真的和你在一起时，他们的存在感如何？
you're actually with them if you say
如果你说，
like listen Jack is the loveliest person
杰克是
in the world and Jack Loves sharing his
世界上最可爱的人，杰克喜欢分享他的
vacation trips and there's a little bit
度假旅行，虽然
but he's a sweetie then jacks off the
他有点自恋，你知道，但他是个好人，那么杰克就没问题了，对吧？但
hook right I think though that what n
我认为，
what social media has become is it has
社交媒体已经变成了……（此处原文似乎有误，无法翻译）。
taken PE Once Upon a Time and you're
你
probably even you're you're not so young
可能年纪也不小了，
that you wouldn't remember this but I
应该还记得这件事，但我
remembered it as a full grown ass woman
作为一个成年女性仍然记得。
is that I can tell you that if I go
我可以告诉你，如果
backwards to when I first heard about
追溯到我第一次听说
social media I was already in my 40s at
社交媒体的时候，我已经四十多岁了。
that point and um and I remember looking
我记得当时
at it and I was already studying
我在研究
narcissism and I said oh God I I and it
自恋，然后我就想，我的天哪！感觉
was really like it was almost like
就像是“
Houston we have a problem kind of thing
休斯顿，我们遇到麻烦了”一样。
someone else had shown it to me and I
有人给我看过社交媒体，我
thought to myself this isn't going to
心想，这东西不会
create more narcissist but once upon a
制造更多自恋者，但
time for a narcissistic person to get
以前，自恋的人想要获得
validation they'd actually have to have
认可，就得去
a shave in a shower and get out of the
淋浴刮胡子，走出家门。
house you couldn't just sit home and get
你不能只是待在家里就获得
validation you had to go go to work get
认可，你必须去工作，
it in a family sphere get it in your
在家庭圈子里获得认可，去
town bar or Pub or something like that
镇上的酒吧或酒馆之类的场所获得认可。
but it wasn't going to come home from
但
you just sitting on your ass at home
你不可能只是坐在家里自拍就获得
taking pictures of yourself cuz I don't
认可，因为我不
know if you've ever tried to take a
知道你有没有试过。
picture of yourself with the camera
用相机自拍，
you're either going to catch your head
要么会拍到头，要么会拍到
or your mouth like that's how we used to
嘴，以前我们就是这么拍的，对吧？
try to do it right so now there was a
现在
tool for these people to have a
这些人有了个工具，就像个
megaphone to say look how wonderful I am
扩音器，可以炫耀自己有多棒。对于本来就
narcissistic this was going to harness
自恋的人来说，这简直是火上浇油，就像是给
fire that was already burning but I keep
已经燃烧的火焰加了助燃剂。不过，我还是把他们关
in the house though isn't it which is
在家里，不是吗？听起来，让
be them wandering around the streets
他们待在家里比在街上游荡更安全。是啊，
yeah well the point is what keeping oh
关键在于，把他们关在
keeping them in at home rather than but
家里而不是让他们出去。但
I still think that what it did though is
我仍然认为，这引出了
now we get into a bigger philosophical
一个更大的哲学
question this many people depicting
问题：这么多人都在展示自己的
lives that are look how much better my
生活，炫耀“看我的
life is than yours look how together I
生活比你的好多少”、“看我多么成功”、“
am look how great I'm doing while that
看我多么了不起”。虽然这
might be something the narcissistic
可能是自恋
people will do to offset their sense of
者用来掩盖自身不
insecurity because that's sort of the
安全感的一种方式，因为不安全感是
core wound in narcissism there are other
自恋的核心创伤，但还有其他
vulnerable people who are watching that
脆弱的人也在观看这些
content who are not narcissistic but
内容，他们并不这么认为。 有些人自恋，但又
already feel like they don't measure up
觉得自己不够好，
and we've created this really messy
我们创造了一个非常混乱的
space of people who already devalue
空间，这些人本来就贬低
themselves looking at these lives far
自己，看着别人的生活
better than theirs and wondering what's
比自己的好得多，然后纳闷自己到底哪里出了问题。
me roughly one in six people have a
大约六分之一的人都有
podcast so I was just
播客，所以我就在
wondering I mean that that many people
想，这么多人
think they have something that
觉得自己有这么
interesting to say right so um and like
有趣的东西要说，对吧？嗯，就像
I said everybody's trying to put their
我说的，每个人都想表达自己的
voice out there their vacation pictures
观点，他们晒度假照，晒
out there their breakfast pictures out
早餐照，这并不代表
there are not narcissistic I think in
自恋。我认为在
some cases I I don't think we should
某些情况下，我们不应该过度
over pathologize what has become a new
解读这种新的
way of interacting I've got it's
互动方式。这很
interesting I have children my my my
有意思，我有孩子，我的
daughters are now both in their early
女儿们现在都二十出头了，
20s and I'll watch their facility but
我观察她们，但
they're it's not I see what they're
她们的
doing it's not narcissism it's actually
行为并不是自恋，而是
communication and they're staying in
沟通。她们
touch with a very large net of widely
与
spread friends and there is a lot of
分布广泛的朋友保持联系，彼此之间有很多
intimacy there so I think young people
亲密关系。所以我认为，随着
whose cognition kind of also grew with
认知能力的提升，年轻人会
it they use it in a more sort of
利用这种方式。 以一种更
seamless way listen what's it been
无缝的方式，听着，它存在多久了？
around now we're we're going to soon
我们很快就要
come come 20 years around 20 years since
迎来
social media has been around right we're
社交媒体诞生20周年了，对吧？我们
rounding that horn soon we're going to
很快就要走到这一步了。我们将
get it's going to take a minute to get
获得
the data we're going to get our first
第一批数据，这些
set of data from the kids whose lives
数据来自那些从出生到
through ad adolescence that data is
青春期一直被记录下来的孩子们。这些数据
going to be very telling I don't think
将非常具有启发性。我不认为
it's created more narcissism I think
它制造了更多的自恋者。我认为
we've always had grandiose narcissists I
我们一直都有夸大自恋者。我
think they make history they've been our
认为他们创造了历史，他们一直是我们的
leaders they're the people we've always
领导者，是我们一直以来
looked to they've been the town mayor
仰望的人，他们一直是镇长等等。
whatever I think what it's all it has
我认为它所做的只是放大了
vulnerable narcissism and it's really
脆弱型自恋的问题，
blown it up because the vulnerable
因为脆弱型
narcissistic people get super resentful
自恋者在
when they perceive other people as
看到别人
having these awesome lives that they
拥有自己没有的精彩生活时会感到非常怨恨。
don't and they get more angry and this
更愤怒，这有点
is sort of the Advent of the Internet
像是网络
troll a lot of that is explained by
喷子的出现，很多时候可以用
vulnerable narcissism so where does
脆弱型自恋来解释。那么
narcissism come from then this is one of
自恋从何而来呢？这是个
the big questions it from what you said
大问题。根据你刚才说的，
there I assume it comes there might be a
我猜它可能源于某种
genetic component that's brought out by
遗传因素，这种因素在
our childhood or so we're all born with
我们的童年时期就被激发出来了。我们生来就有
a temperament right I don't know if
一种气质，对吧？我不知道
you're an only child if you have
你是独生子女还是有
siblings or anything youngest of four
兄弟姐妹，
you're youngest of four okay so this is
你是四个孩子中最小的，好吧，这对
harder for you do you would it' be
你来说可能更难。你会觉得
interesting for you to talk with them is
和他们谈谈很有意思吗？你的
that and your your your parent whoever
父母，或者你们
was parents whoever around every one of
身边的人，
you you and your siblings had slightly
你们每个人，包括你的兄弟姐妹，
different personalities from the day you
从出生那天起就略有不同的性格，这种性格
were born and that rolled out in early
在
childhood so you'll see that one kid
幼儿时期就显现出来了。你会看到有的孩子
who's just easy breezy from the day
从出生起就轻松自在，
they're born you'll some sometimes see
有时你也会看到有的
that kid who's just a clenched up ball
孩子从
of nerves from the day they're born
出生起就紧张兮兮，
you'll see that kid who just doesn't
你还会看到有的孩子一刻也不想
want to chill for a minute from the day
放松。 从
they're born that stuff is called
出生那天起，这种特质就存在，
temperament and what we know about
我们称之为气质。我们对
temperament is that there are certain
气质的了解是，某些
temperaments and those that make a child
气质类型会使孩子在
more biologically vulnerable a little
生理上更容易受到伤害，
bit more difficult to soothe they may be
更难安抚，他们可能更
more they just sort of need more right
需要照顾，
so they're more of a demand on a
对照顾者的要求也更高。
vulnerable temperament if that comes up
如果这种更容易受到伤害的气质与一个
against an environment that's at all
充满
invalidating trauma neglect other
否定、创伤、忽视、其他
adversities chaos domestic violence
逆境、混乱、家庭暴力、
substance use in the family um and even
家庭成员滥用药物，甚至是
emotional abuse with a child is just
情感虐待（例如，对孩子说“
being told stop sit down shut up why
停！坐下！闭嘴！”“为什么
can't you be like your sisters right
你不能像你姐姐们一样？”）的环境相结合，
that com that combination can actually
实际上会
set up a real risk for developing
增加孩子发展出
narcissism so that's pathway one but
自恋的风险。这是途径一。
pathway two and this is actually coming
途径二，这实际上源于
of Amsterdam it's fascinating work and
阿姆斯特丹大学一位名叫埃迪·布鲁曼（Eddie Bruman）的学者的一项非常有趣的研究。这项研究引人入胜，
he is studying more sort of how do we do
他正在研究另一种
what's the other pathway well the other
途径。另一种
pathway and other folks like Masterson
途径，像马斯特森（Masterson）等人
and others have written about this which
已经对此进行过研究，那
is the overvalued child these are the
就是被过度重视的孩子。这些
children who are told you're more
孩子被告知…… 你
special than any other child not that
比其他任何孩子都特别，不是说
you're special but you are more special
你很特别，而是你
than him and him and her so you
比他、他、她都特别，所以你
shouldn't have to wait in a line you're
不用排队，你
more special you should get the teacher
更特别，你应该选你
you want you should get everything you
想要的老师，你应该得到你想要的一切。
want those children often they don't
这些孩子往往不
learn to self Soo they often aren't as
学会自律，所以他们通常不太能
well regulated they actually kind of
控制自己的情绪，他们实际上会
believe the hype that the parent is
相信父母的吹捧，这对
giving them which is not doing them any
他们没有任何
favor favors and Bromans is suggesting
好处。布罗曼斯认为
that this could sort of be a
这可能是
adult narcissism you I'm guessing you
成年后自恋的一种预兆。我想你
need that temperament on board I think
需要这种性格。
if you had a sweet tempered kid that
如果你有一个性格温和的孩子，
constantly being told that they're
不断被告知他们很
special actually might leave the sweet
特别，实际上可能会让他们
tempered kid feeling a little bit guilty
感到有点内疚，
actually but the kid with that more
但那些性格比较脆弱的孩子可能会
of they might buy into the hype so you
接受这种吹捧。所以你会看到一条通往
adversity you have the one pathway of
逆境的路径，一条通往……的路径。
sort of these are kids who are told
这些孩子被告知“
you're great you can anything you want
你很棒，你可以做任何你想做的事，我们会为你
we'll do anything you want let's go on
做任何你想做的事，走吧”。 在
this vacation here's this device but
这个假期里，这里有个装置，但
there're off also kids that are often
也有一些孩子在
very emotionally undernourished they're
情感上严重缺乏滋养。他们
not they're not um their emotions are
的情感
not valued they're not reflected they're
不被重视，不被关注，
not mirrored so these are kids who are
没有得到反馈。这些孩子虽然得到了很多东西，
get get get but it's a very tenuous
但他们的存在非常脆弱，
existence because they're still not in
因为他们仍然无法
touch with their emotional World which
与自己的情感世界建立联系。这种联系必须
has to happen in child otherwise you
在儿童时期建立，否则
don't get that um that so you don't get
你就无法获得
that atlas of your own emotions right so
情感的地图。所以，
those tend to be the two primary p
这通常是两条主要的
Pathways
路径。当然，
now not every kid who goes through those
并非每个经历这些
Pathways will be will become
路径的孩子都会变成
narcissistic in fact the ma vast
自恋者，事实上，绝大多数孩子都
majority will not so I think that the
不会。所以我认为
this it's very complicated and what we
这非常复杂，我们
call it's very it's it's
称之为
multi-determined it's a very
多重决定因素，它是由
multi-determined series of Pathways to
一系列多重决定因素共同作用的结果，最终导致
what leads to adult narcissism and
成人自恋。
because of that I always say narcissism
正因如此，我总是说，自恋的
is one of those stories we can always
故事我们可以
tell backwards but is really difficult
倒叙，但很难正
to tell forwards don't show me your
叙。别给我看你的 一个
17-year-old who is who is has a lot of
17岁的孩子，他
attitude and won't empty the dishwasher
态度很差，不肯把洗碗机里的碗碟拿出来，
and calls you names and don't ask me if
还骂人。别问我
he's narcissistic I usually tell those
他是不是自恋，我通常跟这种孩子的
parents call me in 10 years and in 10
父母说，十年后再来问我。
years you're going to see if this
十年后你们就能看出他是不是真的像
down into a decent guy you mentioned
你说的那么自恋，或者他会不会像其他青少年一样，努力摆脱父母的束缚，最终变成一个正派的人。你提到
that narcissism exists on a spectrum so
自恋是一个连续谱，那是不是
does that mean that someone can be a
意味着有些人可能只是有点
little bit narcissistic I would say
自恋？我觉得
somebody can have milder narcissistic
有些人可能表现出的自恋程度比较轻。
presentation so what I mean by milder
我说的
the mild narcissistic people the best
轻度自恋，最贴切的
adjective I could use they're annoying
形容词是：他们很烦人，
they're emotionally immature they're
情绪不成熟，肤浅，
vapid and and they're also very
空洞，而且非常以
self-centered so these are people when
自我为中心。这些人一旦
they're having a problem they expect the
遇到问题，就希望
world to stop for them take their calls
全世界都为他们停下脚步，接他们的电话，
talk to them for hours but the day
跟他们聊上几个小时，但一天
finally comes that you need your friend
下来，他们却什么都不想做。 当你需要朋友的时候，
they're nowhere to be seeing like oh I
他们却总是不见踪影，好像在说“哦，我
don't have time for this so it can feel
没时间陪你”，所以这种关系会显得
like a very very imbalanced relationship
非常不平衡。和
and when you're with them the mild
他们在一起的时候，轻度
narcissist can actually be kind of fun
自恋者其实也挺有趣的，对吧？
right they're they're like let's go to
他们会说“咱们去
this new hot hip whatever blah blah blah
这个新潮的夜店玩吧”之类的，他们很风趣，会笑，会跳舞，喜欢
attention seeking could be fun for a
引人注目，这种行为可能一开始挺有意思，
minute but there it would be very
但过不了多久就会变质。
relationship with someone like that be
和这样的人建立长期稳定的关系非常困难，
difficult to raise children with someone
和这样的人一起养育孩子也很难，被这样的人
difficult to have been raised by someone
抚养长大也会非常艰难。
like that are narcissists more
自恋者在
successful professionally yes they're
事业上更容易成功吗？是的，他们
much more successful that's the problem
更容易成功，这就是问题所在。
and not I mean again I and I'm not going
我的意思是，我不会
to make this a blanket statement but I'm
一概而论，但我
going to tell you now that they are
现在要告诉你，
they're more ambitious success is life
他们的确更容易成功。他们更有野心，成功对他们来说就是生死攸关的事，
or death to them right because it's
因为成功
validation it's the it's the it's the
是他们的价值，是
blood that flows to their psyche so the
他们精神的血液，所以对
stakes are much higher for them the rest
他们来说，成功的风险要高得多。
of us we want to succeed but at the end
我们其他人也想成功，但
of the day we would say I've got my
最终我们会说，我有
family I got my friends I got enough
家人，我有朋友，
money in the bank I got some food in my
银行里有足够的存款，我吃饱穿暖，这就足够了。
belly like I'm good but for them it is
但对他们来说，成功是
it's the air in their lungs so they're
他们生命中不可或缺的一部分。所以他们
more represented in leadership they are
在领导层中更有代表性，
they make more money especially
他们赚的钱也更多，尤其是
narcissistic men make more money than
自恋的男性比随和的男性赚的钱更多。
um they're more successful at dating um
他们在约会方面也更成功。
they're more successful and
他们更成功，但
unfortunately the way our economy is set
不幸的是，我们的经济体制让
up it is set up so that the narcissistic
自恋的
people win narcissism and capitalism go
人更容易获胜。自恋和资本主义
together really well because it's a
非常契合，因为这是一个
competitive system that rewards the
竞争体系，奖励那些贡献
person who does the most and we don't
最大的人。我们不
look at process we look at outcome and
看过程，只看结果。在
be when any anytime you have an outcome
任何以结果为导向的
heavy metric narcissistic people are
指标体系中，自恋的人
always going to win
总是会赢。
I'm thinking about some of the greatest
我想到一些
changed the world you know Apple being
改变世界的伟大公司，比如苹果。我们经常
them oftentimes when you hear about how
听到
these people treated other
这些人是如何对待他人的，
um it sounds like the narcissistic
听起来很像
characteristics that you described
你之前描述的自恋特征。
earlier you know but then we often
但我们常常
excuse that because of what they brought
因为他们给世界带来的成就而原谅他们——
into the world the great Innovations the
伟大的创新，
great companies they built how they
他们创建的伟大公司，他们如何
helped change the world how they maybe
帮助改变世界，他们如何
led us through or out of
带领我们走出
War so
战争。那么，
what do you say to that is it sometimes
你对此有何看法？为了他们给世界带来的贡献，
worth their narcissism for what they
他们的自恋有时值得吗？
gave the world so here's here's a rub I
我
completely agree with what you're saying
完全同意你的观点，
I actually think that some of the
事实上，我认为一些最伟大的
greatest Innovations greatest creativity
创新和创造力……
in fact many wartime presidents and
事实上，许多战时总统和
prime ministers were it had to be
首相都带有
narcissistic right and might have gotten
自恋倾向，他们或许能带领
Count's people through messes might have
人民渡过难关，或许能
made the had the decisive postures that
采取必要的果断立场，
were necessary that might have made the
或许能做出
real really really kinds of um difficult
真正艰难的
corporate decisions that needed to be
商业决策，而这些决策往往
make with little regard for how the
不顾及会给人民带来怎样的
human beings were going to get hurt
伤害，
treated people way pushed them to an
对待人民的方式近乎残酷，甚至将他们逼到
inhuman limit and then there was this
非人的极限。然后，
thing that came out of it was it worth
问题来了：这一切值得吗？
it I mean now we're in now we're in
我的意思是，现在我们进入了
philosophy honey and I'm a
哲学领域，亲爱的，我是个
psychologist but but suffice it to
心理学家，但总而言之，
say you know there's some there's always
你知道，一直以来都有这样的
been talk like even inventors like Tom
讨论，比如像托马斯·
Alva Thomas Alva Edison wasn't a was not
阿尔瓦·爱迪生这样的发明家，他并不是
a nice guy right some archival res
一个好人，对吧？一些档案资料显示，他
SE loving these light bulbs right would
热爱电灯泡，对吧？换作
someone else have done it it's a mood
其他人会怎么做？这是一个关键
point he did and
点，是他做的。
so I think the Innovations are important
所以我认为创新很重要，
I think narcissistic people are built
我认为自恋的人天生适合
for Innovation they're grandiose they're
创新，他们胸怀大志，他们是
dreamers they want the agile they want
梦想家，他们追求敏捷，他们想要
to do the big thing they want to be on
成就大事，他们想要…… 他们渴望站在
the big Tech stage and have all the
科技大舞台上，沐浴在聚光灯下，
lights on them and have all the
吸引所有人的
attention while they have the Beautiful
目光，拥有精美的
video and the simple thing and they want
视频和简洁的产品，而这似乎
that that is their everything and what I
就是他们的一切。但我
tell people is we're never never going
告诉人们，我们永远无法摆脱
to have a world without them we have
他们，
gotten lots of cool stuff in our lives
我们生活中有很多美好的东西都来自
from them just don't marry
他们，只是别和
them is it possible to be the person on
他们结婚。那么，是否有可能成为站在
the stage to build the incredible thing
舞台上，打造出不可思议的产品，
to have the insane ambition to put
拥有将小型电脑装进口袋的远大抱负，
all of that and not be a narcissist I
同时又不自恋呢？我
fully believe there absolutely 100% I
完全相信这是可能的，百分之百。但我
think it's harder though I really really
认为这更难，真的，我
do I think that the empathic CEO is a is
认为有同理心的CEO就像
a unicorn it's tough that you know and
独角兽一样稀有。你知道，这很不容易，
because they're they're answering to so
因为他们要对很多方面负责，对
shareholders they're answering to rank
股东负责，对普通员工负责，
and file they're answering to management
对管理层负责。
it's I wouldn't want that job I I'm a
我不想做那样的工作。我是一个
very agreeable empathic person and I I I
非常随和、有同理心的人，我必须
got to tell you i' I'd rather do any job
告诉你，我宁愿做任何工作也不愿做那份工作。
than that one it sounds I'd love the
听起来…… 我很想
money but I it's it sounds terrible and
要钱，但这听起来太可怕了。
I think that the kind of shapeshifting
我认为这份工作需要那种善于变通、像
and chameleon like qualities that
变色龙一样的特质，而同理
empathic person would get a bit more
心强的人更容易被
swallowed up in that job because if you
这份工作吞噬。因为如果你
actually stopped to care about everyone
真的不再关心
you were serving in that position you
你服务的每一个人，你很快
would burn out real fast the not caring
就会精疲力竭。
I think is what actually can protect a
我认为，正是这种漠不关心才能保护身处
person in that position and that's not
这个位置的人。当然，这并不是
to say all CEOs are narcissistic though
说所有CEO都是自恋的，虽然
a lot are because it's a competition at
很多CEO确实如此，因为
the end of the day it is a competition
归根结底，这是一场竞争。
at the end of the day and narcissistic
自恋的
people are built for competition they're
人天生就适合竞争，
built for it because they have to win at
他们必须不惜
any cost the rest of us are probably
一切代价赢得胜利。而我们其他人可能早就放弃了。
like I'm out you know yeah a lot of
你知道，很多
Industries are a zero some game not
行业都是一场零和博弈，
business generally isn't but when I say
商业通常不是这样。但我说的
zero some game I mean there's you know
零和博弈是指，
when um one person does well that kind
当一个人做得好的时候，就意味着
of means that someone else is not going
其他人
to do well so I'm thinking about some
做得不好。所以我想到一些
Industries even one of my companies
行业，甚至包括我所在的公司之一——
third web we realize that it's kind of a
第三方网络，我们也意识到这一点。 这有点像
winner takes all industry in the same
赢家通吃的行业，就像
way that like Amazon is like there's one
亚马逊一样，只有一个
Amazon and they dominate the whole of
亚马逊，它
them pretty much all the market share
几乎垄断了所有市场份额；
and with Google there's one Google and
谷歌也只有一个谷歌，
the nearest competitor probably has 5%
最接近的竞争对手可能只有5%的
of the market share so there are
市场份额。所以
elements in business where it is pretty
商业中确实存在赢家通吃的现象。
think the person who is most ruthless
可以想象，那些最冷酷无情、
most willing to cut ethical Corners most
最愿意走道德底线、最
willing to put profits over people is
愿意把利润置于人命之上的人，很可能会最终
probably going to rise to the top that's
胜出。
right so you know generally espe at
没错，通常情况下，
least in the short term in the short
尤其是在短期内。
term and but the thing is then they'll
但问题是，他们最终会获利，他们
cash out yeah all their bad ethics will
所有的不道德行为都会让他们付出代价，
catch up with them or their bad ethics
或者说，他们的不道德行为最终会让
will catch up with they'll end up in
他们锒铛入狱。
jail which we see a lot we do we see it
我们经常看到这种情况。
and I think for some people it was a was
我认为对某些人来说，这是一场
it was a worthy gamble because they
值得一试的赌博，因为他们有
could have potentially won at all right
可能赢，
or they or they truly believed they were
或者他们真的相信自己可以
going to get away with it and I think
逍遥法外。我认为，这就是
that that's when we use the word
我们用“傲慢”这个词来形容他们的时候。
deepest level is I'm going to do the bad
最深层次的问题是：我要做
thing and I'm going to get away with
坏事，而且我要逍遥法外。那么
it what about money um does money make
金钱呢？金钱会让人
you more
更
narcissistic here's where it gets to be
自恋吗？这就引出了
an interesting conversation and I write
一个有趣的话题，我
about this actually more in my other
在我的另一
book and don't you know who I am where I
本书里对此有更详细的论述，你不知道我是谁吗？我在书中写道：金钱
I money breeds privilege money breeds
滋生特权，金钱滋生优越感，
entitle entitlement what I call the sort
我称之为“
of phenomenon of feet that never touch
脚不沾
the ground right if people have enough
地”的现象。如果人们有足够的
money they're whizzed to airports and
钱，他们就可以被快速送往机场和
cars they don't stand in the TSA line
汽车，不必像我们其他人一样和芸芸众生一起排队安检，
of us do they're taken to the best hotel
他们被带到最好的酒店
suites they are they don't think about
套房，他们不必考虑
where their next meal is coming from
下一顿饭在哪里，食物会送到
it's brought to them they don't they
他们面前，他们
don't do the all the the stuff that the
不必做
rest of us do they don't tolerate the
我们其他人做的所有事情，他们无法忍受
indignities and they don't have to
屈辱，也不必
regulate the same way so when a person
遵守同样的规则。所以，当一个人
has money for long enough that feet
拥有足够多的金钱，以至于“脚
never touching the ground creates what
不沾地”的状态，就会产生所谓的
entitlement was that maybe [__] but
特权和优越感。也许吧。 混蛋，但
maybe not I think it's also that bubble
也许不是。我觉得还有他们那种小心翼翼、
wrapped way that they go through life
小心翼翼的生活方式，
like they actually don't understand how
就像他们根本不会
to use the self checkout at Target did
用Target的自助结账机一样。
you hear the Paul piff study from the
你听说过保罗·皮夫（Paul Piff）的研究吗？
University of yeah he's great by the way
他很棒，顺便说一句，
he's wonderful which well we did so many
他很了不起。我们做了很多
which study are you referring to um the
研究，你指的是哪一项？嗯，就是那个让
one where people are made to feel
人们感觉更
wealthier and when they feel wealthier
富有，然后发现
they were more likely to endorse
他们更倾向于支持
unethical decisions such as stealing
不道德行为的研究，比如偷
office supplies stealing candy people
办公用品、偷糖果。那些感觉更
who were made to feel wealthier also
富有的人也
gave less to charity people who were who
更少捐款给慈善机构。那些感觉更富有的人更倾向于
happiness through feelings that were
通过以
self focused such as through Pride um
自我为中心的情感来表达快乐，比如骄傲、
contentment and amusement and people who
满足和愉悦。而那些
felt less wealthy were more likely to
感觉不那么富有的人则更倾向于
agree with statements that were focused
同意以
on others that's right which kind of
他人为中心的言论。没错，这似乎
suggests that being wealthier and
表明，更富有、
feeling wealthier makes you more of an
感觉更富有会让你更像个
[__] makes you more of an [__] it
混蛋，
makes you more self-referential right so
让你更自恋，对吧？所以
I think that you know does that make
我觉得，你知道，这说得通吗？
sense surprising you think it be the
你觉得结果正好相反，这很令人惊讶吗？一点也不，一点也不。
because I think that again Paul's
因为我认为…… 保罗的
research is great by the way he's
研究很棒，顺便说一句，他很
wonderful he actually did another
了不起。他之前做过一项
research study where he studied um he
研究，
looked he went to busy intersections in
他去橙县繁忙的十字路口观察，当时
Orange County he's a professor UC Irvin
他是加州大学欧文分校的教授。他们
and they'd go to busy intersections stop
去的是那些有停车
signs not red lights and he found that
标志（而不是红灯）的繁忙路口，他发现，
people who drove luxury cars were far
开豪华车的人
stop sign and people compared to people
比开中档车的人更不愿意在停车标志前完全停车。这真是太
level cars I mean it was fascinating so
有趣了。
there's and and there's there's at least
至少有十
a dozen published studies that show that
几项已发表的研究表明，
narcissistic people drive more
自恋的人开车更
dangerously so it's an interesting kind
危险。这是一个很有意思的研究成果。
of an accumulation but per the money
至于金钱
part I don't believe like if a person
方面，我不认为如果一个人
was a full grown adult 30 35 years old
已经30、35岁，性格
agreeable warm self-aware person and
温和友善，有自知之明，而且收入很高，那么金钱会让他
think you would turn them
变得
narcissistic I do think you might
自恋。但我认为金钱可能会
undercut that self awareness because
削弱他的自知之明，因为
they may be sort of pulled out of the
他可能会脱离
world that the rest of us live in so
我们其他人生活的世界。 人们
there might be unrealistic expectations
可能对世界抱有不切实际的期望，
for how the world like why are we
比如“我们为什么要排队？”
waiting in this line I'm like well
我会想，那是
that's because what we do is wait in
因为我们排队是
this line because they've come out of it
因为他们已经摆脱了困境。
but they're not cruel about it they're
但他们并不冷漠，他们会想“为什么
like why are these dumb people making me
这些蠢人要让我
wait in line so it's not a
排队？”所以这不是一种
dismissiveness it's almost like how is
轻蔑，而更像是“
this so inefficient there's almost a
这怎么这么低效？”，
there's like a disconnect I guess so I
感觉像是存在某种脱节。所以我
wouldn't say money I think what he's
不会说是金钱的问题。我认为他所
showing is that money creates a
展示的是，金钱会滋生
self-centeredness right as you thought
自我中心。正如你所想，情况
it might go the other way but I think
可能恰恰相反，但我认为
that we sort of double down on sort of
我们反而会加倍地执着于
keeping it and we there's there's an
维持金钱，而且金钱非常
importance I mean money is is the
重要。我的意思是，金钱是
ultimate source of narcissistic Supply
自恋供给的终极来源，
because it delivers power it delivers
因为它带来权力、带来
admiration it delivers a greater
赞美、带来更大的性
likelihood of getting sex or getting
机会，
laid it delivers all kinds of stuff so
它能带来各种各样的东西。所以
for a narcissistic person the quest of
对于自恋者来说，追求
for money is the the shest quick ticket
金钱是
way to get this thing called
获得这种所谓的“
narcissistic Supply so you'll often see
自恋供给”最快捷径。因此，你经常会看到……
them attempting to do that by any means
他们试图用尽一切手段，
possible so but they but they're driven
但他们最终还是被
to the money I don't think that the
金钱驱使。我不认为
money is what makes people rot and I
金钱是导致人堕落的根源，我
think the bubble wrapping at that point
认为那种过度的自我保护让
makes them entitled it's a different
他们变得自以为是。这是另一个
conversation how do you know if you are
话题了。你怎么知道自己是不是
narcissist like does a narcissist know
自恋者？自恋者自己知道吗？有没有什么
they are one is there a narcissist test
自恋测试？
one can do I don't there's about five to
我不知道。目前市面上大约有五
six tests out there that are designed to
六种测试旨在
detect narcissism in its various ways
检测各种形式的自恋，但
all of them have flaws like I said and
正如我所说，它们都有缺陷。这甚至
it's not it's not even fully the fault
不能完全归咎于
of the test because this is a very
测试本身，因为自恋
difficult thing to measure right we're
很难衡量。
at we're trying to measure things that
我们试图衡量的是一些
are not socially desirable right that's
不符合社会期望的东西，这
really tough to measure so a lot of the
真的很难。所以很多
narcissism tests will measure things
自恋测试会衡量一些
like some entitlement assertiveness um
诸如优越感、自信、
self-importance that people may not find
自我重要性之类的东西，人们可能不会觉得这些很
as offensive but the research actually
冒犯，但研究实际上
shows that narcissistic people
表明，自恋者会
overestimate their empathy
高估自己的同理心，
and underestimate their negative effect
低估自己的同理心。 他们
on other people they do not have a clear
对他人的负面影响在于，他们无法清晰地
look at themselves they really have an
认识自己，对
almost deluded sense of who they are and
自身以及在世间行事的方式有着近乎妄想的认知。
how they go through the world so when a
所以，当
person says to me I think I'm
有人对我说“我觉得自己很
narcissistic I always say hold the
自恋”时，我总是会说“等等，
presses you need to tell me a little bit
你得先跟我说说你
about you because there's a lot of
自己的情况”，因为很多
people out there who think of themselves
人之所以认为自己
as narcissistic because they're in
自恋，是因为他们
relationships with narcissistic people
与自恋的人在一起，这些人
who have told them over the years years
多年来一直告诉他们“
you are such a selfish person because
你太自私了”。
this unfortunate person is doing simple
可怜的人只是做了一些简单的
things like saying hey could we go where
事情，比如问“嘿，我们能不能去
I want to go for dinner once or you I
我想去的地方吃一次晚饭？”或者“我想跟你
want to talk about my feelings and then
谈谈我的感受”，然后
their narcissistic partner saying oh my
他们的自恋伴侣就会说“
gosh you're so selfish and they're
天哪，你太自私了”。他们
really sort of indoctrinated into this
实际上已经被灌输了这种
idea or gaslighted into this idea that
观念，或者说被煤气灯效应操控，认为自己身上有自恋的特质。
them once we clear the decks of that is
一旦我们排除了这些因素，是否存在
there a subset of people out there who
一部分人，他们本身就是自恋的，
are narcissistic and are kind of in some
并且在某种程度上
awareness like this might be who I am
意识到了这一点呢？ 做我自己，
yes and we call them self-aware
没错，我们称他们为有自知之明的
narcissistic people they're out there
自恋者。他们确实存在，
some of them view narcissism as their
有些人甚至把自恋视为自己的
superpower they say like don't take this
超能力。他们会说：“别
away for me this is why I've got the
夺走我的优势，这就是我的优势所在，
edge this is why I close the sale this
这就是我能拿下订单的原因，这就是
is why I'm the man and one client was
我为什么是行家。” 有个客户说：“
like I'm the man like oh my gosh like a
我就是行家。” 我的天哪，简直像个
six-year-old but okay do people men come
六岁小孩。好吧，真的有人会来找
to you women come to you and say I am a
你，男人、女人，然后说自己是
narcissist yes I've had that happen it's
自恋者吗？是的，我遇到过这种情况，虽然
not common I can count on one hand the
不常见，一只手就能数过来。
you agree with them and they I in about
你同意他们的说法吗？我大概花了
an hour
一个小时。是的，
yeah what was were they how did they
他们是怎么
figure out they were a narcissist what
意识到自己是自恋者的？
were they saying they might have read
他们说了些什么？
they might have read my books or more
他们可能读过我的书，或者
more likely saw YouTube video they might
更有可能看过我的YouTube视频，或者
have you know sort of again seen my
看过我的
content someone might have said that to
内容，有人可能跟
them and then they looked it up on
他们说过类似的话，然后他们上网搜索，觉得“这有点像我”。
me but they did in many ways rationalize
但他们在很多方面都为自己的行为辩解，比如…… 这就是
it saying this is why I always close the
为什么我总是会说“这就是我”，
deal this is who I am like you know what
你知道吗？
was it don't hate the don't hate the
别恨人，别恨
player hate the game they would try that
玩家，要恨游戏规则。他们会对
kind of stuff with me and I'd say but
我耍这种花招，我会说“但
your behavior is offensive like this is
你的行为很冒犯人，这不对，
not okay what you're doing what you did
你
you're doing on an ongoing basis to your
对你的
spouse or partner is not okay and so
配偶或伴侣所做的一切是不对的”。所以
they would have that awareness like
他们会意识到这一点，就像
almost like from a checklist yeah like
在检查清单一样。是
yeah I don't care that much about
啊，我不太在意
people's feelings and yeah I guess I
别人的感受，我
kind of think the rules don't apply to
觉得规则对
me they'll have that awareness it's
我不起作用。他们会意识到这一点，这
pretty uncommon like I said most
很不常见。就像我说的，大多数
narcissistic people Veer into this idea
自恋的人都会
of they overestimate their goodness and
高估自己的善良和
generosity underestimate how um how
慷慨，低估别人对他们的
negatively they're viewed by other
负面评价。那么，
people so let's talk then about the
我们来谈谈
impacts of narcissism on relationships
自恋对人际关系的影响，
particular what kind of people do
特别是
narcissists attract in relationships and
自恋者在人际关系中会吸引什么样的人，以及
what kind of people are attracted to
什么样的人会被
narcissists so it's such a good question
自恋者吸引。这真是个好问题，
I'm so glad you asked it what kind of
我很高兴你 问它，
people do they attract everyone's
他们会吸引什么样的人？每个人都会被
attracted to narcissistic people they're
自恋的人吸引。他们
Charming they're charismatic they're
魅力四射，
confident they're in research has shown
自信满满。研究表明，
they're often rated as more attractive
他们通常
than other people they take good care of
比其他人更有吸引力。他们注重身材，博学
their bodies they know lots of
多识，对时尚
interesting things they're so concerned
无比关注，甚至会说他们
about hiped that they are like they know
知道哪些
the cool restaurants they all of us have
很棒的餐厅。我们都
been indoctrinated to think that these
被灌输了一种观念：这些
are the people were supposed to be
人才是我们应该
dating right who says no to charm
约会的对象，对吧？谁会拒绝魅力、
Charisma and attractiveness me maybe but
风度和吸引力呢？也许我会，但
just nobody else would do that so we're
其他人不会。所以我们都会被
all attracted to them right until and
他们吸引，对吧？
even with the vulnerable narcissistic
即使是脆弱的自恋
folks you'll say really someone's going
者，你可能会说，真的有人会被
to be attracted to Sullen and resentful
阴郁和怨恨的人吸引吗？嗯，他们
you first meet meet them many times a
初次见面时并非如此。很多时候，
vulnerable narcissistic person looks
脆弱的自恋者看起来
like a vulnerable child who needs to be
像一个需要被拯救的脆弱孩子。
rescued so if you like rescuing people
所以，如果你喜欢拯救人
or puppies or any small vulnerable
、小狗或任何脆弱的小
creature that's going to seem actually
动物，那么他们实际上会
very attractive to you so we're all
非常吸引你。所以我们都会
attracted to them what about what are
被…… 那么，
they attracted to in us they're what
他们到底被我们身上的什么吸引呢？他们被我们
they're attracted to in US is our supply
吸引的，就是我们的“供给”。“
now Supply can mean different things to
供给”对
different narcissistic folks classical
不同的自恋者来说意义各不相同。经典的
sorts of Supply or are we attractive if
供给方式是，如果
we're attractive if we have some form of
我们有吸引力，或者我们有一定的
social status if we have have resource
社会地位，或者我们拥有资源，
if we have connections the things that
或者我们有人脉，这些都能
would get them Supply here's where it
成为他们的“供给”。
gets wonky because the question
问题就出在这里，因为“
attractiveness is what attracts people
吸引力”这个问题本身就有点
it's almost the wrong question the more
问题，它几乎是错误的。
deep question is what gets people stuck
更深层次的问题是，是什么让人们深陷
in narcissistic relationships because
于自恋关系中？因为
narcissistic relationships start strong
自恋关系的开始往往非常强烈。
these are people who are running their
这些人
marathon like they're just like go and
就像马拉松比赛一开始就全力冲刺的人，他们会说：“加油，你！”
you this is these can often feel like a
这常常让人感觉像
fairy tale it is is it's glamorous and
童话故事一样，充满魅力，令人兴奋，约会也很有趣，
attuned they may be very attentive they
他们非常善解人意，非常关注
focus on you and they figure what's
你，他们会琢磨什么
going to work for you if they really
对你有效。如果他们真的
want to keep you close it's they want to
想和你保持亲密关系，他们就会
they want to get you and they want to
想方设法得到你，而且要
get you quick because then you're like a
尽快得到你。 因为那样的话，你就如同玻璃罩
butterfly underglass then they've got
下的蝴蝶，被他们牢牢
you captured because after all this good
抓住了。在经历了所有这些美好的事情之后，
stuff happens you've bought in you might
你已经完全投入其中，你
even be dubious for a while saying oh
甚至可能会怀疑一段时间，心想“哦，这似乎
seems seem too good to be true or I
好得难以置信”或者“我
don't know but then people after about I
不知道”。但大约在
weeks and six months the devaluing stage
六周到六个月之间，贬低阶段就
starts and then it's they've got you
开始了。然后，他们就认定你
right and they they you might get the
成功了，你可能会遇到
passive aggressive digs the
被动攻击、
minimizations
轻描淡写、
the lack of empathy the withdrawing the
缺乏同理心、疏远
withholding and people will say where
和冷漠。人们会问：“
did that first six weeks go to like wait
前六周都去哪儿了？等等，
a minute we had such a good time and as
我们之前玩得那么开心！”随着
the devaluing begins people start to
贬低的开始，人们开始
blame themselves so people who are more
责怪自己。那些更有同理
empathic
心、更宽容、
more forgiving more optimistic these are
更乐观的人，反而更容易陷入困境，
because they're making allowances for
因为他们总是试图为对方开脱。
this they're saying I mean I can't they
他们会说：“我的意思是，我不能……他们很
they were lovely and they did say
可爱，他们也说过
at work but their behavior is
工作压​​力很大。”但他们的行为却
consistently dismissive and rude and so
始终冷漠无礼。于是，
you keep making excuses excuses excuses
你只能不断地找借口，找借口，找借口。
but then there's a few good days
但总会有一些…… 这段关系中偶尔也会有美好的日子，
sprinkled in there so one of the
所以
interesting things is um a lot of people
有趣的是，很多人都
are trying to figure out if their
在试图弄清楚他们的
partners are narcissists h do people in
伴侣是不是自恋者。处于
relationships especially long-term
恋爱关系中的人，尤其是长期
relationships tend to know that they're
恋爱关系中的人，通常知道自己正在和
narcissist or is the n or is the
自恋者交往吗？还是自恋者对
narcissist gaslighted them to the point
他们进行了煤气灯操纵，以至于
that they they don't know until recently
他们直到最近才意识到这一点？
most people did not know because it's it
大多数人以前都不知道，因为
feels like a disloyal thing to know
知道伴侣的这种行为感觉像是背叛。
about your partner many people say I
很多人说“我
love my partner we have built a life
爱我的伴侣，我们一起建立了生活”，但其中也
together there are enough good days that
有足够多的美好日子，让
leave them thinking like there's
他们觉得这段
in these relationships are confused
关系里似乎有什么问题。他们感到困惑。身处这种关系中的人都很困惑，他们会把
everything that goes wrong they're
所有出错的事情都归咎于自己，他们如履薄冰，
walking on eggshells they've in essence
实际上已经把
modified themselves to be exactly what
自己改造成
the narcissistic partner wants but it's
自恋伴侣想要的样子。但这就像一场慢性
a slow burn it's it's a very slow
毒药，一个缓慢的
process of indoctrination I always say
洗脑过程。我总是说
these relationships are Death By A
这种关系就像“
Thousand Cuts because it's just each of
千刀万剐”，因为每件事都是
these things happen slowly over time
随着时间的推移慢慢发生的，
it's almost as a one day you wake up
几乎就像一天之后…… 醒来后
you're like who am like what have I
你会想：我是谁？我
become I'm literally like living in
变成了什么？我简直就像在
service to this other person it's only
为另一个人服务。
in the last 10 years I'd say that
我觉得这仅仅发生在过去的十年里，相关的
there's so much more content and the
内容才变得如此丰富，
internet is more robust with making this
互联网也更加发达，这方面的内容也更加丰富。
and I'm sure people type it in my
我敢肯定，人们会在必应上搜索“我的
partner has no empathy and is really
伴侣缺乏同理心，自以为是，经常
entitled and yells at me a lot Bing and
对我大吼大叫”，
then narcissism pops out at you I think
然后“自恋”这个词就会跳出来。我认为
this really created the revolution of
这真正引发了一场关于“
people saying what is this and even when
这是什么”的革命。甚至在
I wrote should I stare should I go that
我写《我该凝视吗？我该离开吗？》那篇文章的时候（应该
was
是
2015 I think it was we're still in the
2015年），我们还处于
beginning phases there were just maybe
起步阶段，当时市面上可能只有
about a dozen books out there taking
十几本书在探讨
this on and so we it's it's a as more
这个问题。所以，随着更多
information gets out there more people
信息的传播，越来越多的人
are clear
意识到
that this is happening in their
这种情况正在他们的关系中发生。
relationships the hope is the earlier
希望是，
you identify it the less indoctrinated
你越早发现它，就越不容易被它“洗脑”。
the less what we call trauma bonded you
你越少受到我们所说的创伤性联结的影响，就越
become and then the easier it would be
容易
to make clear-headed decisions about how
冷静地决定下一步该怎么做。
you want to proceed you talk about the
你
negative relationships in your books
在书中提到了负面关系的三大特征——“3R”。这三大特征是什么呢？
what are the three Rs so the first is
首先是
rumination okay that the rumination is
反刍（rumination）。反刍指的是
it's an obsessive thinking about the
对这段关系的执着思考，
relationship and it's usually in an
通常是为了
attempt to either say what did I do
反思自己做错了什么、发生了什么、现在的情况，或者
it's a trying to fix it so these are the
试图去解决问题。所以，
relationship with a narcissist will do
和自恋者交往的人通常会做这三件事。当然，
yep I mean they do a lot more but these
他们还会做更多，但这
are three common ones so the rumination
三件是比较常见的。反刍
is a Hallmark characteristic of a person
是自恋型人格障碍患者在这种关系中的典型特征，
essence you're just trying to make sense
本质上，你只是试图理解
of something that makes no sense the
一些根本无法理解的事情。
next R is regret and that regret links
下一个“R”是后悔（regert）。后悔与
to bigger themes like grief people
更深层次的主题相关，比如悲伤。人们
having regret that this is the parent I
会后悔自己拥有这样的父母，却永远无法
loving relationship with them the regret
与他们建立亲密而充满爱的关系；后悔自己
that this is the marriage I created and
缔结了这样的婚姻，却
my children will never get a healthy
无法让孩子拥有健康的家庭。
model of marriage the regret that I've
婚姻模式：我后悔
spent 20 years in this relationship and
在这段关系中度过了20年，结果
whole lot of nothing except that it's
除了
harmed me so the regrets play out even
伤害自己之外，什么也没得到。这种后悔无处不在，无论
big ways and even small ways like why
大事小事都会让我后悔，比如“我当时为什么那样说？”、“
did I say that why didn't I say it that
我为什么不那样说？”。
way and then the last R is it's really
最后一个“R”指的是“
euphoric recall the are being for recall
欣快回忆”。这里说的“
by euphoric recall I mean that people in
欣快回忆”是指，自恋型人格障碍患者有
narcissistic relationships of an uncanny
一种不可思议的
ability to sort of
能力，他们会选择性地回忆
in the relationship to keep
关系中发生的“好事”，并以此来
rationalizing it and justifying it to
合理化和说服
themselves so ba might be in a
自己。比如，你可能和
narcissistic relationship with a person
一个自恋型人格障碍患者在一起，对方在
has really treated them heinously for a
一个月里对你非常恶劣，
month but on one day of that month the
但有一天，当
narcissistic person when they went to
自恋者
the grocery store for the first time
第一次去超市时，他
remembered to bring home two muffins so
记得买了两个松饼回家，这样
that you could have a muffin and the
你就可以吃一个了。你就会想：“
person's like they brought me home the
他们给我带回来的是
best blueberry muffin wasn't that
最好的蓝莓松饼！”“他们给我带回来的
thoughtful they brought me home a muffin
松饼也太贴心了吧，
we had muffins together so the euphoric
我们一起吃了松饼！” 欣快
recall is the over focus on those good
回忆是指过度关注那些美好的
experiences as a way in essence to
经历，本质上是为了
create this sort of psychological buyin
建立一种心理上的认同感，
so then you can maintain the status quo
从而维持现状。
for people in narcissistic relationships
对于身处自恋型关系中的人来说，
it's not as those they're waking up
他们并非醒来
saying this is a hellscape I want to get
就说“这是人间地狱，我要逃离”，而是醒来后感到
confused I feel like I'm never enough
困惑，觉得自己永远不够好，无论做什么都不够好，无论说什么都不够好，
say is ever they're not listening to me
他们根本不听我说话，到底发生了什么？
what is going on maybe I'm not being
也许是我表达得不够
clear enough maybe there's something
清楚，也许是我自身出了问题。这就是
wrong with me so that's the confusion
困惑的
element so it's not like everyone's
根源。并非每个人
saying I want to get out of this there's
都说“我要离开”，而是因为他们之间有很多过往，有很多
experiences together so people again and
共同的经历。人们感到
they're also confused because there's
困惑的另一个原因是，既有
good things that happen and bad things
好事发生，也有坏事
that happen and that's what creates like
发生，这就形成了
I said this thing called the trauma
我所说的创伤
bonded relationship so people might even
联结关系。所以，人们或许能够
be able to say like there's something
意识到这段关系存在问题，甚至能够清晰地
even be able to articulate these are the
表达出这些
problems in the relation relationship
问题所在，
but the idea of leaving this
但这种“创伤联结关系”的概念却难以形成。 离开这段
relationship fills me with an absolute
感情让我感到极度
sense of panic would would a narcissist
恐慌。自恋者会利用这种不
play to that insecurity and that um that
安全感吗？嗯，这段过往
history well the narcissistic person
经历，嗯，自恋者
created the insecurity and they they
制造了这种不安全感，他们会这么做，
will because the narcissistic person is
因为自恋者是
an expert tactician right because that's
策略高手，对吧？因为
what they bring to relationships is
他们带入感情的就是
tactics and so they are very expert at
策略，所以他们非常擅长，
knowing like ah your wound is
比如，啊，你的伤口是被
abandonment piece of cake so if you say
抛弃，小菜一碟。所以如果你说“我
I I can't do this my out the
做不到”，
narcissistic partner say okay cool let's
自恋的伴侣会说“好的，酷，我们把它叫做小
call it quiz you'll like that's not what
测验”。你会喜欢的，这不是
I wanted them to say I wanted them to
我想要的，我想要的是他们会
say they were going to fight for the
说他们会为这段
relationship you see what I'm saying
感情而战。你明白我的意思吗？
like they it's so interesting because
这很有意思，因为
and part of the reason narcissistic
自恋
people are so successful is because
者如此成功的部分原因是
they're so socially perceptive they have
他们非常善于察言观色，他们缺乏同理心。
no empath social perceptiveness and
社交洞察力和
empathy are not the same thing what do
同理心不是一回事。它们是什么？
they social perceptiveness is kind of
社交洞察力是指能够
being aware of reading the room
察言观色，了解
understanding what people need
人们的需求，
understanding what makes them tick and
了解他们的动机和
what they want and then strategically
想法。 想要什么，然后策略性地
giving it to them to keep them on the
满足他们，以此来控制他们，
chain or keep them in the position you
或者让他们保持在你
need them in that's not
需要的位置上。这并非
empathic manipulation you Ed the word
同理心操纵，你之前用这个词
earlier on to describe
来描述
narcissism there's two types of
自恋。
manipulation you speak about which is
你提到的操纵有两种类型：一种是
the the sort of normal manipulation
正常的操纵，
which I think we all do in our own ways
我认为我们每个人在
when we're trying to get our way with a
试图
deal or with sales or with someone or
达成交易、销售或与他人
whatever when we're trying to haggle for
相处时都会以自己的方式进行这种操纵，比如讨价还价以获得
a discount whatever it might be and then
折扣等等；另一种是
there's this pathological ipulation
病态操纵，它
which seems to be a little bit different
似乎略有不同。是的，
M yeah pathological manipulation is that
病态操纵是指
there's absolutely no regard for the
完全不顾及给
harm it's bringing the other person you
对方带来的伤害，你
really are giving absolute Primacy to
真正将
your own needs and then making the other
自己的需求放在首位，然后让
person think that this truly is good for
对方认为这对他们真的有好处。
them this isn't as simple as I'm going
这并非像“我要把
to sell this car to someone maybe it's
这辆车卖给某人，也许这
not the right car for them this is
辆车并不适合他们”那么简单。这
really around psychological stuff and
实际上涉及心理层面，比如当
it's with somebody where listen you're
你
going into a sales relationship you
进入一段销售关系时，你应该
understand what the sort of the codes of
了解
that relationship are they're trying to
这种关系的规则，他们试图……
sell you something you're trying to
推销员会向你推销东西，而你却在犹豫
decide if it's right for you we don't
它是否适合你。我们不会把
try to think of our intimate and our
亲密关系和
familial relationships as sales models
家庭关系当作销售模型，
so our guard is not up in the same way
所以我们不会像推销员那样提高警惕。
and yet the same tactics are being
然而，同样的伎俩却被用在了我们身上，
brought and we're sort of bargaining on
我们实际上是在就一些关乎
things that are matters of the heart and
内心、关乎
matters of closeness and compassion so
亲密和同情的事情讨价还价。所以，
it's again the narcissistic person is so
自恋者非常
skilled at leaving the other person
擅长让对方
feeling that the thing they sacrificed
觉得他们所牺牲
or gave up was in their best interest
或放弃的东西是为了他们自己的利益。
and and ultimately the narcissistic
最终，自恋
person is so self-centered that anything
者是如此以自我为中心，他们所做的一切都是为了
serve them projection I've heard this
满足自己的投射需求。我听过
phrase used a few times like he's
几次“他把
projecting onto you or she's projecting
投射投射到你身上”或“她把投射投射到
in the context of narcissism what is
自恋者身上”这样的说法。那么，什么是
projection so projection is CL is a
投射呢？投射是一种
primitive defense that any of us can use
原始的防御机制，我们每个人都可以使用，
and we do use all of us engage in
而且我们确实都会使用。
projection we engage in projection when
当我们内心
some of that uncomfortable unconscious
某些不舒服的、无意识的
stuff inside of us is getting activated
东西被激活时，我们就会进行投射。这些东西
it's often shame or oriented and then
通常是羞耻感或其他负面情绪，然后
we'll accuse someone of something that
我们会指责别人做了我们自己认为是自己的事情。
we're actually feeling like an
其实感觉很不
uncomfortable feeling that's projection
舒服，这就是投射，
we all EX um how you might project onto
我们都经历过。嗯，你可能会把这种感觉投射到
me okay uh we're in a we're in a
我身上。好吧，我们现在是一对，
relationship and I'll say something like
我会说：“
who are you texting Stephen like why
斯蒂芬，你在跟谁发短信？
what do you like you're so shady like
为什么？你这么阴险，
you know why don't you show your show me
为什么不给我看看
your phone like what oh my gosh Stephen
你的手机？”我的天哪，斯蒂芬，
like what the hell you need so many you
你到底在干什么？你需要那么多
need all the girls to like you don't you
女孩喜欢你，对吧？
like that's what you're all you're about
这就是你的全部，给
show me your phone show me your phone
我看看你的手机，给我看看你的
show me your phone now
手机，现在
guess who's got a side piece that would
猜猜谁有小三？
be me oh really oh there's a life hack
是我。哦，真的吗？哦，
for you Stephen okay so you're you're
斯蒂芬，给你个小窍门。好吧，你没
insecure because you know that you're
安全感，因为你知道你是
Stephen not insecure I I'm doing a bad
斯蒂芬。没安全感？我在做
thing are you still
坏事吗？你还在
pretending no I am no longer in a
假装？不，我已经
relationship okay so we're done that's
分手了。好吧，我们结束了，那是
because you cheated on me even though
因为你背叛了我，虽然不是我，但确实是
didn't but it was me but now I can go be
我。现在我可以
with my new
和我的新
guy so but it's I'm giving giv you like
男友在一起了。所以，我给你…… 举
such a loow hanging fruit example it's
个简单的例子，
anytime we might accuse someone of lying
比如我们自己撒谎的时候可能会指责别人撒谎，
when we're lying we may accuse somebody
我们自己不安全的时候也可能指责别人缺乏
of um even being insecure when we're the
安全感，对吧？我们自己感到不自在的时候也可能
one feeling insecure right we'll accuse
指责
someone of being uncomfortable when
别人感到不舒服。
uncomfortable and all of us have
我们每个人都有
different stuff we project about because
不同的投射对象，因为
all of us have different sort of
我们每个人都有不同的
psychodynamic histories right well
心理动力学经历，对吧？
narcissistic people do this all the time
自恋的人总是这样。
let me give you sort of a sense of what
让我来给你描述一下
a narcissistic person looks like despite
自恋者的内在心理机制：尽管他们外表光鲜
all the shiny charismatic Charming
亮丽、魅力四射、
arrogant grandiose stuff on the outside
傲慢自大，但他们的内心，
what's in them is the best I can
我能想到的最好
describe it is a volcano right and that
形容就是一座火山，对吧？这座
volcano the magma and the gases and the
火山的岩浆、气体和
lava is shame and it's insecurity well
熔岩就是羞耻和不安全感。这
that's not very perfect looking is it so
看起来并不完美，对吧？所以，
all these defenses the grandiosity and
所有这些防御机制，自大、
the arrogance and the charm and all the
傲慢、魅力等等，
rest of it is like a manhole cover a big
就像一个巨大的
manhole cover that covers the volcano so
井盖，盖住了…… 火山爆发，所以
all that insecurity doesn't exist I'm
所有的不安全感都不存在了，
I'm just the smartest person you know
我就是最聪明的人，你知道吗？
right so they get to show up as perfect
所以他们可以表现得完美无瑕，卓越
extraordinary but things can kick that
非凡。但一些事情会让他们崩溃，比如
manhole cover off criticism negative
批评、负面
feedback their friend doing better than
反馈、朋友比
them their new Venture not succeeding um
他们做得更好、新项目失败、
them not getting something that they
没得到
wanted some form of frustration well
想要的东西等等，这些挫折都
that means they're not perfect the
意味着他们并不完美。就像
manhole cover gets nudged the gases in
火山爆发一样，火山爆发，岩浆中的气体喷涌而出。
the lava o out what does that look like
这看起来像什么？看起来
it looks like anger it looks like
像愤怒，看起来像
projection you accuse the other and this
投射。你指责别人，而这种情况
happens to them 20 times a day CU nobody
一天发生在他们身上20次。没有人
lives a perfect life we get disappointed
过着完美的生活，我们总是会失望。
all the time there's traffic on the
高速公路堵车，
freeway there we had to wait for the
我们不得不等
elevator the people at the coffee shop
电梯，咖啡店的人
screwed up our order our our public
搞错了我们的订单，或者我们的
offering didn't go well it could be big
IPO失败了。可能是
things it could be small things it
大事，也可能是小事，这都
doesn't matter but each time the manhole
无关紧要。但每次火山爆发，他们
cover gets nudged that grandiose
那宏伟的
exterior gets tinged and they they
外表就会蒙上阴影，然后他们会向
explode on others and that often looks
别人爆发，这通常看起来
like projection and that projection
像是投射。这种投射
allows them to maintain that idealized
让他们能够维持理想化的
interior can they take feedback
内心世界。他们能接受反馈吗？
narcissists like do they listen to the
自恋者会听取意见吗？
do they no they they can't they really
不会，他们根本听不进去。
narcissistic person may may tiny bit
他们唯一可能稍微
listen to feedback is if it comes from
听取一点反馈的情况，是反馈来自比
them because narcissistic people are
他们权力大得多的人。因为自恋者是
very hierarchical climbing creatures
非常讲究等级、喜欢向上爬的生物。
right so let's say they're getting it
假设他们正在听取反馈，
the CEO's up here and there's some sort
CEO在这里，
of P level person here and they admire
P级员工在这里，他们很崇拜
the CEO the CEO is giving them
CEO，CEO在给他们
feedback they will listen because they
反馈，他们会听，因为他们
want to be him they want to be with him
想成为CEO，想和他在一起，想站在
whoever the CEO is right but I so they
CEO旁边。所以他们可能听进去
may get some of it but they're still
一部分，但仍然会
going to hear it
听到一些杂音，这些
as there'll be this noise that's
杂音会让
blocking them out from hearing all of it
他们听不到全部内容。
so it might be
所以，他们的顺从可能只是为了达到目的，而不是
them actually going ah okay no yeah
真正地去理解。
they're not not integrating it into
他们并没有真正接受反馈，只是敷衍了事，甚至可能
might even think like God this person's
心想：天哪，这个人真是个
such a dick I I could do their job so
混蛋，我比他做得好多了。
much better they're so lucky they got
他们真幸运能到
there I'm going to get there but they
那里，我也会到那里，但他们，他们，
they again they also Envy this person so
他们又一次嫉妒这个人，所以
they are listening but like you said it
他们听着，但就像你说的，这
is exactly what you said it's compliance
完全是顺从，而不是“
versus the sense of let me listen to
让我听听
this and I can promise you what this
这个，我可以向你保证，
person's going to do if they're in a
如果这个人有伴侣，他会怎么做”的想法。
relationship they're going to go home
他们会回家对
and rage at their partner because they
伴侣大发雷霆，因为他们
had to have that feedback session
不得不接受那次反馈。
they're going to find a more vulnerable
他们会寻找更脆弱的
Target because they can't attack that
目标，因为他们不能攻击
CEO and they'll go and find someone else
CEO，所以他们会去找其他人发泄
to rage at a partner a person on the
怒火，比如伴侣、
subway train a family member friend
地铁上的陌生人、家人、朋友等等。
someone else I heard this word
我又听到“
gaslighting again it's a word I've heard
煤气灯效应”这个词了，我经常听到这个词，
a lot but I I'm not necessarily really
但我不太
clear on what the definition of
清楚
gaslighting is but from reading your
煤气灯效应的定义是什么。不过从你的
work I hear that narcissists gas light
作品来看，我听说自恋者
people a lot a lot right what is
经常对别人进行煤气灯效应，对吧？煤气灯效应到底是什么？
gaslighting so gaslighting it's simplest
简单来说，煤气灯效应
it's a power play it's a form of
是一种权力游戏，一种
emotional abuse and it's a tactic
情感虐待，也是一种策略。
gaslighting is predicated on a
煤气灯效应建立在一段
relationship that's ostensibly car
关系之上。 表面上看，煤气灯效应的
characterized by trust so that's why
特征是信任，所以
strangers can't gasl at you in the same
陌生人无法
way as an intimate partner a trusted
像亲密伴侣、值得信赖的
colleague a family member even a person
同事、家人，甚至是像
with expertise like an attorney or a
律师或
physician could Gaslight you right
医生这样的专业人士那样对你进行煤气灯操控，
because there's a there's a presumption
因为存在
of trust so you're going to listen to
信任的推定。所以你一
the gaslighter initially what the
开始会听信煤气灯操控者的话。
The Gaslight head person's perceptions
煤气灯操控者会做的就是质疑被操控者的感知、经历、记忆，
experiences memories even reality that
甚至是
never happened I never said that you're
从未发生过的现实。他们会说：“我从没说过那样的话，你在
making that up that you're we never went
编造，我们根本没去过那里。”
there so now this person's a little
这时，被操控者会感到
confused because their reality is saying
困惑，因为他们的现实是：是的，
yeah we did yeah we did so initially a
我们去过，我们去过。所以，一开始，被操控
person will fight back against a gas
者会反击煤气
light they'll say we absolutely went
灯操控，他们会说：“我们绝对去过
there do you want me to show you the
那里，你想让我给你看
pictures on my phone then we go to the
我手机里的照片吗？”然后，煤气灯操控进入下一个
next step of gaslighting the gaslighter
阶段。操控者
doesn't want to see the pictures on your
不想看你
phone they just want to overpower you
手机里的照片，他们只想控制你。
this isn't about evidence this is about
这与证据无关，而是关乎
them overpowering you so they'll say
他们如何控制你。所以他们会说：“看，这是我
look here's the pictures on my phone and
手机里的照片。”
then the gas fighter won't say well
然后，煤气灯操控者就会反击。 他们不会说“好吧，
you're right we did go there instead
你说得对，我们确实去过那里”，而是会
they'll say oh my gosh you are the most
说“我的天哪，你是
Petty human being I've ever met is this
我见过最斤斤计较的人！这就是
what it is you're just going to go on
你们的相处方式吗？你只是想翻
your phone to find the pictures to prove
手机找照片来证明什么？这就是我们
something to me is that what this
之间的
relationship is I don't know that I want
关系吗？我不知道我是否还想继续这样的
even be in a relationship like this now
关系！”
this poor person who's being gaslighted
可怜的被煤气灯操纵的人会
is thinking I just showed them the
想：“我只是给他们看
pictures to prove a point and now I'm
照片来证明我的观点，现在我反而成了
the bad one and so they're and they
坏人。”他们
trust this person so they think well
信任这个人，所以他们会想：“
maybe I am doing something bad maybe I
也许我真的做错了什么，也许我真的太斤斤计较了。”
am being petty but gaslighting doesn't
但煤气灯操纵并非一次性的，而是反复发生的。
over again it's an indoctrination
这是一个潜移默化的
process that leaves the gaslighted
过程，让被操纵的
person utterly confused completely out
人彻底迷失方向，
of their minds doubting themselves and
精神崩溃，开始怀疑自己，并最终
they start to believe the critiques then
相信那些批评。然后，
the gaslighter will tell them things
操纵者会告诉他们：“
like you're crazy you're stupid you
你疯了！你很蠢！你
don't remember things right maybe you
记性不好！你是不是
have dementia do you think you should be
得了老年痴呆症？你是不是应该去看心理
in therapy you might need to be on
医生？你是不是需要
medication like by the time the
吃药？”等等等等。
gaslighter is done with with someone
煤气灯操纵者对某人完全
they've lost all sense of they don't
失去了自我，
they don't trust themselves at all and
他们不再信任自己。
so if they don't leave the relationship
因此，如果他们不离开这段关系（
and some people don't they are then sort
有些人确实不会离开），他们就会
of in this again this form of servitude
再次陷入这种奴役状态，
gaslighting person almost relying on
几乎完全依赖自恋者或煤气灯操纵者来
them to lead them through reality so
引导他们面对现实。
it's almost like utter submission at
在这种状态下，他们几乎完全屈服，
gaslighter gets to dictate reality and
煤气灯操纵者可以支配他们的现实。随着
then over time there's there's this
时间的推移，
there's this tactic that narcissistic
自恋者和
and other abusive people use called dar
其他虐待者会使用一种叫做“
darvo stands for deny attack reverse
否认、攻击、反转
victim and offender it's a construct
受害者和施害者”的策略。这是
that was developed by Dr Jennifer fried
詹妮弗·弗里德博士提出的一个概念。
so what the narcissistic person will in
自恋者会
a very skill I mean in a cruy skillful
非常巧妙地（我是说非常巧妙地）利用被煤气灯操纵者的行为，比如，
way do is if the person the gaslighted
如果被操纵者
person ever attempts to push back on
试图反驳
something that the narcissist is does
自恋者所做的任何事情，
done like you came you said you were
比如“你
going to be home by 9:00 last night you
昨晚不是说好9点到家吗？” 你
didn't get home till 1: in the
凌晨一点才回家，那个
morning the narcissistic prison will
自恋的家伙会
deny said that's not true I came yeah I
否认，说这不是真的，我回来了。没错，我的确没在
home at any 1 in the morning but again
晚上九点到家，但我绝对没到凌晨一点。但话说回来，
like what is your problem like what do
你到底有什么毛病？
you do like you read the ADT guide all
你整天都在看防盗指南，就为了
day to see what time I come in the door
看我几点回家？
and you know what like I can't believe
你知道吗？我简直不敢相信
that this is my life I work so hard to
这就是我的生活。我那么努力工作，就是为了让
keep us in this fabulous house I work so
我们能住在这么棒的房子里。我那么
hard so you can stay home and I'm the
努力工作，就是为了让你能待在家里，结果我却成了
bad guy like I can't even believe that
坏人。我简直不敢相信
this is the issue like you put me
问题竟然出在这里。你让我经历了这么
through so much reverse victim and
多，受害者和
offender he was out till 1: in the
加害者的角色互换。他凌晨一点才回家，
morning and he knows it but now he shut
他自己也知道，但现在他却拒绝和我
down the conversation it is an Insidious
说话。这是一种阴险的
dynamic because done enough you
动态，因为如果这种行为持续下去，你
literally strip another person of their
实际上就剥夺了另一个人的
reality and that is unacceptable to me
现实感，这对我来说是不可接受的，这
that's absolute abuse do you see this
绝对是虐待。你经常看到这种情况吗？这种
the dynamic that once it had name to it
动态曾经被赋予了一个名字，
when the word is used right most people
当这个词被正确使用时，大多数人却
use this word wrong that whole process I
用错了。整个过程……
is used correctly it's powerful it
正确使用“煤气灯效应”这个词，它蕴含着强大的力量，它
captures a unique interpersonal Dynamic
捕捉到了一种独特的人际互动模式，这种模式会
that really eats people from the inside
从内而外地摧毁一个人。
out I hear it I see it all the time by
我经常听到、看到这种情况，无论是家人、伴侣、
workplace you name it and it really
职场伙伴，还是其他任何场合，都可能发生。它真的会让人崩溃，
messes people up because they they feel
因为人们会觉得自己
like they've lost their minds and they
失去了理智，甚至
feel like they can't trust themselves
无法信任自己。
and I think that's a terrible thing to
我认为这对别人来说是一种极其恶劣的行为。
do to someone what should you do if
如果
you're being gas
你正在遭受煤气
lit when you know what it is and someone
灯效应的折磨，而你又知道它是什么，并且有人
starts to gas light you they literally
开始对你进行煤气灯效应的操控，你应该怎么做？他们会彻底
deny your reality right you have to take
否定你的认知，对吧？你必须
a step back and say that's not what
退后一步，告诉他们事情并非如此，
happened but you don't say it to them
但你不要直接告诉他们。
the importance with gaslighting is you
应对煤气灯效应的关键在于
don't engage with the gaslighter you now
不要与施虐者互动。既然你已经
know you're being gaslighted which
知道自己正在遭受煤气灯效应的操控，这
means the other person in that
意味着对方
interaction has the capacity to Gaslight
有能力对你进行煤气灯效应的操控。
you so what that means is from your side
所以，
you need to shut it down and that means
你需要阻止这种行为，这意味着
no longer engaging does that make so
不再与他们互动。这是否意味着
that you cannot keep engaging with them
你不能继续与他们互动，
because they're going to pull you down
因为他们会把你一步步拉入深渊？
further and further yeah they're gonna
是的，他们会的。
it's almost like they're going to pull
这几乎就像…… 他们会把
you down into into being drowned or pull
你拖入深渊，让你窒息，或者把
you into the quicksand so when they
你拉进流沙。所以当他们
start gaslighting I never said that one
开始对你进行煤气灯操纵时，我从没说过一次
playback could be we're having a
回放就能解决问题。也许我们
different experience then and leave it
当时的经历不一样，就此打住。
at that don't go down that slipp SL
别掉进那个陷阱，
don't go down the slope don't say don't
别走下坡路。别说，别
show them the text message don't pull
给他们看短信，别
out the email don't try to prove them
拿出邮件，别试图证明他们
wrong don't engage with them it's it's
错了，别跟他们纠缠。
funny you're asking me this because I
你问我这个问题真有意思，因为我
was recently gaslighted I in relatively
最近也被煤气灯操纵了。就在
recently in a professional
不久前，在一个工作
situation and I'm thinking not me like I
场合，我心想，不是我，我
don't know much but I know this so don't
懂得不多，但我知道这一点，所以别理他们。
but they did I was and I got very upset
但他们确实这么做了，我非常生气。
and in this particular situation it was
在那个特殊情况下，
actually I understand why I got it like
我其实理解他们为什么会这样。你可以把它
think of it as a corporate structure
想象成一个公司体系在对
that was gaslighting me so sometimes
我进行煤气灯操纵。有时候，
very very nice people who work in
在公司体系中工作的人，即使是非常非常友善的人，也会进行
corporate systems Gaslight because
煤气灯操纵，因为
they're trying to prop up the narcissism
他们试图维护
of the corporation but they're decent
公司的自恋。但他们都是正派的
human beings and it was very clear to me
人，这一点我很清楚。
I've seen that happen but in this
我见过这种情况，但在那个
particular case I was being gaslighted I
特殊情况下，我…… 虽然我知道自己被煤气灯操纵了，也
knowing all the tactics it's very
知道所有那些伎俩，但被完全否定
dehumanizing to have your reality
自己的认知是非常不人道的，
completely doubted and so I I did feel a
所以我感到很
sense of upset but I confronted the
生气。但我还是和对方对质，
person I said this is gaslighting and
说这是煤气灯操纵，这样做
it's not okay and I know you're better
不对，我知道你比
than this and they will happen to be
这好得多。他们也确实如此。这次我比较幸运，因为
the gaslighter was not
操纵者不是
narcissistic so we came to a conclusion
自恋型人格，所以我们达成了共识。
but when I've been gaslighted by
但如果我被
narcissistic
自恋型
people I just disengage and I file it
人格的人操纵，我会选择置之不理，把这件事记在心里，
away and say this person is capable of
告诉自己这个人能做到这样那样，没什么大不了的。这种
deep controlling Behavior emotionally
控制行为只能做到这种程度，情感上和
but also I guess physically controlling
身体上都有控制
behavior when we when we often think
行为。我们一想到
about narcissists we think of like sort
自恋者，就会想到
of domestic violence and this kind of
家庭暴力之类的，而这种
thing is that quite typical of a
行为确实是
narcissist to engage in domestic vience
自恋者典型的家暴行为。
so here's we get to an interesting
所以，接下来是一个有趣的
question you're from the UK and I have
问题。你来自英国，我
to say actually of all the countries in
不得不说，在世界上所有国家中，
the world the UK actually has had has
英国的……
taken the front I think the the the
我认为，在
very creating public policies around
制定公共政策以
understanding the psychological elements
理解
of domestic violence it was actually a
家庭暴力的心理因素方面，应该站在最前线，发挥最重要的作用。事实上，
coer of control laws first showed up in
控制胁迫法最早出现在
the UK so I this is my personal belief
英国。所以，
Stephen and this is my personal belief
斯蒂芬，这是我的个人观点，
and I will hold to this personal belief
我将百分之百坚持这个观点：我
100% I believe all domestic abusers are
认为所有家庭施暴者都是
narcissistic without exception and I'll
自恋的，无一例外。我会
tell you why I think that the capacity
告诉你为什么。我认为，一个人如果能对
to tell someone I love you I'm going to
别人说“我爱你，我会
care for you we're in a
照顾你，我们是一对”，
relationship and then to emotionally
然后又在情感上、
physically or sexually assault them
身体上或性方面攻击对方，
that's zero empathy that's tremendous
那就是零同理心，是极度的优越感，是
it's incredible
难以置信的
arrogance that's narcissism there's a
傲慢，这就是自恋。他们
lack of self-awareness there's a lack of
缺乏自我认知，也缺乏
awareness of the other and I think this
对他人的认知。我认为这……
is why so much of the domestic violence
为什么很多家庭暴力
intervention programs they don't work
干预项目都无效？
because how are you going to undo
因为你如何才能改变
someone's
一个人的
narcissism so that's my belief and I
自恋倾向？这就是我的看法。我
know that this has been a this is very
知道这
controversial conversation in the field
在家庭暴力领域一直是一个极具争议的话题。
of domestic violence back in the 70s
早在70年代，就有人强烈反对
there's a real push back on this I don't
这种观点。我
think that anyone who does domestic
认为任何从事家庭
violence work will ever doubt that
暴力工作的人都不会怀疑
there's a personality issue in these
这些人存在人格问题，
folks but the concern was if we made it
但当时的担忧是，如果我们把
about narcissism will pull the focus
焦点放在自恋上，就会
away from their behavior right but I
转移人们对他们行为本身的关注。但我
think the two things go together the
认为这两者是相辅相成的：
behavior is unacceptable I don't give a
行为本身是不可接受的。我不在乎
damn if they're narcissistic and this
他们是否自恋。至于
whole idea of does the narcissism excuse
自恋是否可以成为
the behavior never if behavior is
行为的借口，答案是否定的。如果行为是
unacceptable it's unacceptable I don't
不可接受的，那就是不可接受的。我
care about the backstory because it
不在乎背后的故事，因为这
means it's going to happen again and it
意味着它还会再次发生，而且
always
总是如此。
does narcissism in work how do I know if
在工作中，我如何判断
my boss or my manager or my CEO is a
我的老板、经理或CEO是否是
narcissist and what should I do about it
自恋者？我应该怎么做？
do I quit the job so if you believe that
如果你怀疑
someone you report to a manager or a
你的上司、
boss or someone like that in a job is
经理或类似职位的人是
narcissistic you're going to feel it in
自恋型人格，你就会感受到这种自恋。你会觉得
the sense of you don't feel seen you
不被重视，
don't feel valued you feel like the
感觉不到价值，觉得
workplace is unpredictable you feel like
工作场所难以预测，觉得不
it's unfair that it's inequitable you
公平，甚至觉得心理上不安全。你
might even feel that it's
可能会
psychologically UNS safe you might feel
觉得
that the way people are praised and get
人们获得表扬和认可的方式毫无
have Rhyme or Reason it is inequitable
道理可言，很不公平。工作场所
it might be a very there might be a lot
可能充斥着很多
of Gossip in the workplace those are the
流言蜚语。这些都
things that would suggest a workplace is
表明你的工作场所可能存在问题，
you have you might be working for
你可能正在为一个自恋的人工作。这很难判断，
one it might a lot of this might depend
很多情况可能取决于
on the nature of your organization I
你所在组织的性质。我
always tell people if you suspect that
总是告诉人们，如果你怀疑
you're boss or manager or someone you
你的老板、经理或上司
report to is narcissistic start
是自恋型人格，一定要尽可能多地
documenting the hell out of it because
记录下来，因为
the one thing HR doesn't care is you you
人力资源部门最不关心的就是你。你
cannot roll up to an HR office and say I
不能直接跑到人力资源办公室说…… 我
think my manager is narcissistic you're
认为我的经理很自恋。你
going to need documentation which means
需要做好记录，这意味着
saving emails and text messages and
保存电子邮件、短信、
voicemails and meetings me U minutes of
语音留言和会议记录（比如
meetings and you know you you're going
会议纪要）。你
to need as much information try to avoid
需要尽可能多的信息，尽量避免
meetings alone all that stuff to have
单独开会，所有这些事情都需要
that sort of evidence base if you're at
证据基础。如果你在
a large enough company where you might
一家足够大的公司
be able to switch to work under someone
工作，或许可以换个经理，
else's management especially if you
尤其如果你
still believe in the company some people
仍然相信这家公司的话。有些人
might say I love the organization I
可能会说：“我喜欢这家公司，但我
can't stand working with this person
受不了和这个人一起工作。”
they may find that working with someone
他们可能会发现，换个经理
else will allow them to preserve in the
能让他们继续留在
institution but in a smaller employer or
公司。但在规模较小的公司，或者根本
where that is not possible some people
不可能换经理的情况下，有些人
might try to stick it out the best they
可能会尽力坚持下去，
can but documenting is not going to make
但做好记录并不会让事情变得更
it easier so some people will find that
容易。所以有些人最终会发现，
ultimately if they can't Outlast the
如果他们无法熬过
narcissistic boss or manager which they
自恋的老板或经理（这种情况很
often can't they will look for other
常见），他们就会另谋出路。
employment some people also find a lot
有些人也能从
of solace in collaboration so just
合作中获得慰藉。所以，仅仅
because you work for a narcissistic
因为你的
manager doesn't mean you're colleagues
经理自恋，并不意味着你的同事也自恋。还有
are narcissistic and there's some
一些
interesting research suggesting that
有趣的事情值得探讨。 研究表明，
relationships can come when the
当
leadership is narcissistic but the the
领导者是自恋型人格时，反而可能出现一些非常强大的合作关系，
teams actually come together even
团队反而会更加
stronger it's almost like they're United
团结，就像他们为了
against a common enemy I want to make
共同的敌人而团结起来一样。我想
sure I've given enough advice to someone
确保我给那些正在与自恋者打交道的人提供了足够的建议。
narcissist all of the things that you've
你对
said to them ring true they they can
他们说的一切都很有道理，他们能
relate to everything you've
感同身受。
said are you telling them to get out of
你是在告诉他们要离开
that situation no and it's something is
那种环境吗？不，
very very important to me is that people
对我来说，非常非常重要的一点是，人们
don't feel compelled that they have to
不应该感到非得
get out cuz I can't always get out and I
离开不可，因为我并非总能离开。我
think if we said if we put that forth as
认为，如果我们把离开作为
the only pathway then people who can't
唯一的出路，那么那些无法
get out might say that now what I'm just
离开的人可能会说：“难道我只能
supposed to sit here and suffer and the
坐在这里受苦吗？”
answer to that's
答案是否定的。
no in in in my in my book what I talk
在我的书中，我谈到的
about is this idea if you're gonna if
是这样一个观点：如果你因为某种
like this right for whatever reason
原因（比如
could be a family member and you you
家庭成员）而选择继续维持这种关系，即使
don't you still don't want to fully walk
你仍然不想彻底
away from your family of origin it could
离开你的家人。 原因可能
be a long-term marriage and you've got
是长期的婚姻，你们有
minor children or there's Financial or
未成年的孩子；也可能是经济或
cultural reasons it might be a job
文化方面的原因；可能是
you've had for a long time and you're
你做了很久的工作，
not financially in a position to step
经济上无法放弃；也
away from it it might be a friend you've
可能是你
had a long time your reasons are yours
认识很久的朋友。你的理由是你自己的。
and so I always say to people you must
所以我总是告诉别人，
never feel pressure unless it's
除非危险，否则永远不要感到压力。我们先把
dangerous let's take dangerousness out
危险排除
of the equation right you don't feel
在外，好吗？你不会
compelled to do what people say it's
被迫听从别人的话。
going to be harder if you stay it is
如果你继续待下去，会
going to be harder because you're still
更难，因为你仍然会受到
being exposed OS to their manipulative
他们操纵、否定、不友善、令人不安、破坏
destabilizing behavior however the first
稳定的行为的影响。然而，
step the key step is what I call radical
第一步，也是关键的一步，是我所说的彻底
acceptance this is not going to change
接受。这种情况不会改变，就是这样。不会有“
someday better it's not going to get
总有一天会好起来”这种说法。
better when he gets a promotion it's not
他升职了不会好转，
kids grow up your mom's not going to get
孩子长大了也不会好转，你妈妈不会随着
soften with age this is it folks you now
年龄增长而变得温柔。就是这样，朋友们。你们现在
know what this looks like it is not
知道这是什么样子了。
going to change substantially their
他们的行为不会有实质性的改变。 情况
behavior is not going to change substant
将会发生根本性的改变，
stantially so if you're going to stay in
所以如果你要继续待下去，
it your workarounds are going to be
你的应对方法将
based on knowing that you have to have
基于你必须抱有
very realistic expectations now what
非常现实的期望这一认知。然而，
happens though is when people initially
当人们最初
have this level of radical acceptance
达到这种彻底接受的程度时，
they have a tremendous amount of grief
他们会经历巨大的痛苦，
because a lot of Hope was keeping them
因为很多希望支撑着他们继续
going I thought it was going to get
下去。他们以为
better someday I thought maybe that
总有一天情况会好转，以为总有一天会到来。而
someday would come the staying means
继续待下去意味着
that someday is not going to come and so
总有一天不会到来。这
that means that you're not as once you
意味着，一旦你
radically accept you're not as surprised
彻底接受了现实，你就不会再
by their behavior cuz a lot of people
对他们的行为感到惊讶，因为很多人在
over years or decades they're like I
多年甚至几十年的时间里，无数次地感到疲惫，他们会说：“我简直
can't believe they did that I can't
不敢相信他们会这样做，我简直不敢
believe they did I'm like can we just
相信他们会这样做。” 我会想：“我们能不能
stop that part and say of course you
就此打住，告诉自己：‘当然，你
believe they did it in fact we could
相信他们会这样做。’事实上，我们完全可以根据‘
have set a clock by the idea that they
他们会这样做’这个想法来推断出时间。这是其中很重要的
would have done it that's a big piece of
一部分，
this but the grief of letting go of what
但放下
you wanted these things to be that's its
你对这些事情的期望所带来的痛苦，
own process and grief takes time but you
本身就是一个过程，而痛苦需要时间。但你
know as you come around through through
知道，当你最终……
that as you come around the bend on that
当
you really do radically accept you need
你真正经历这一切，最终你会彻底意识到你需要
some tools and probably the biggest tool
一些工具，而最重要的工具或许就是与那些
who are healthy empathic attuned
健康、有同理心、善解人意、反应迅速、富有
responsive compassionate and respectful
同情心且尊重他人的人建立社交联系。
whether that means you make you you
无论这意味着你要主动结交
might have friends who already are this
朋友，还是通过
into therapy you might join a support
接受心理治疗来增强这种联系，或者加入互助
group you might meet friends at work
小组，或者在工作中结识朋友，
there's many ways you might try to do
有很多方法可以尝试。
this but you're going to need it because
但你肯定需要这些工具，因为
if you're going to stay you're going to
如果你想继续这段婚姻，你
need spaces where you're not gaslighted
需要一个不会被精神操控的空间，
you're going to need spaces where you
你需要一个能让你被
are seen where you are valued where you
看见、被重视、被
are cherished that becomes the pathway
珍惜的空间。这才是
to surviving and then it doesn't feel
生存之道。当然，
good to feel like you're in a marriage
感觉自己在一段婚姻中只是
where you're phoning it in for the rest
敷衍了事地度过余生肯定不好受，
of your life but you know people people
但你知道，人们常说，
say that now that I'm not as surprised
现在我
by their behavior it's a little more
对他们的行为不再那么惊讶了，所以更容易
bearable I've constructed a rich life
忍受。我
almost around this marriage and I just
几乎围绕着这段婚姻构建了一个丰富的生活，我只是把它
sort of you know view that as sort of
看作是一种……
the kind of annoyance in the side of the
房间角落里传来一阵烦躁，
room that it is some people people say I
有些人说，我
happen to adore my my sister but I can't
碰巧很爱我的妹妹，但我
stand my narcissistic parent and you
受不了我那自恋的父母，你
know I so but I'm going to stay in touch
知道的，就是这样。但我会
with them so I can also have the family
和他们保持联系，这样我也能参加
gatherings that matter to my sister but
对妹妹来说很重要的家庭聚会。但
I no longer have conversations with my
我不再和我的
mother or one person I know said she
母亲说话了。我认识的一个人说，她
would regularly visit a narcissistic
会定期去看望她自恋的
father because nobody else would give
父亲，因为没人搭理
him the time of day and he he needed a
他，他需要一些
little bit of assistance she said I'd
帮助。她说，我会
set a timer 90 minutes max once the 90
设定一个90分钟的定时器，90分钟一到，我就吓了一跳。他说，他
jump he'd always yell at her she said
总是会对她大吼大叫，但
but better to yell at 90 minutes than at
90分钟时吼总比
3 hours either way he was going to yell
3小时后吼好，反正他都会吼。
so people get into this space of
所以人们会逐渐
accepting what this is and its
接受这种状况及其
limitations some people over time may
局限性。有些人随着时间的推移，可能最终还是会
still decide to leave but not at that
选择离开，但不是
moment but staying and not radically
立刻离开。如果继续待下去，不彻底
accepting it will destroy you can you be
接受它，最终会毁了你。你能
happy in a relationship with a
和自恋者保持一段幸福的关系吗？
narcissist do you think you can be happy
你认为你能幸福吗？
but not with the relationship so you
所以你
don't think you can be happy with the
觉得这段关系不会让你快乐，
relationship I don't think so no I I
我不这么认为。不，我
think you can see it with its
觉得你能看到它的
limitations and and I think you know
局限性。而且，我认识一些
I've met people who said who have told
人，他们跟我讲过很多
me everything about
关于
narcissistic um Partners who said they
自恋伴侣的事，他们说他们
happen to be able to do this one sex
碰巧能做到一件
thing I love and so that's just I mean
我喜欢的事，所以，我的意思是，其他的一切都很
all the rest of it's awful we can't end
糟糕，反正我们也不能分手，
anyhow so we do the sex thing and it
所以我们就做这一件事，这
works for me um some people will say we
对我来说很有效。有些人会说，我们都
both love watching period dramas and
喜欢看古装剧，所以他就是
that's they're my person to do period
我的
dramas with someone else said we we
古装剧搭档。还有人说，我们都
obsessive about collecting antique
痴迷于收集古董
fountain pens and I really can't stand
钢笔，我真的受不了
spending time with him but we get
和他待在一起，但当
excited when we find a new pen someone
我们找到一支新钢笔时，我们又会很兴奋。
else said he's a hell of a Scrabble
还有人说，他是个拼字游戏高手。
player you find the one or two things
你找到一两件适合你们的事情，这样你们就
that work for you is it happy I mean
快乐了吗？我的意思是，
again we're getting back into philosophy
我们又回到了哲学层面，
there that sense of it you know what's
你知道，
happy on that point of sex are
在性方面，什么是快乐？
narcissists better in better depends on
自恋者更好吗？更好取决于
what you call Better I actually just
你如何定义更好。实际上，我只是……
recently did there's a big piece in USA
最近《今日美国》上有一篇关于这个话题的大篇幅文章，
Today on this that I'd been interviewed
我接受了采访。文章里提到，
for they are very performative lovers
他们是表演型的情人，
they are as you can imagine they like
正如你所想，
they they they almost want Applause
他们几乎在
after the sex act right because they
性爱后就渴望得到掌声，因为他们
need admiration and validation so they
需要赞美和认可。所以，他们
actually can be rather invested in
会非常投入地
getting a partner off because they want
让伴侣达到高潮，因为他们想要
to be told oh my gosh you're the best
听到“天哪，你真是个好
lover ever they might want to be very
情人”之类的赞美。他们可能很喜欢对着
like mirror sex so they can see their
镜子做爱，这样就能看到自己的
body or your body because it's all again
身体或者对方的身体，因为这一切都带有
very performative but some narcissistic
很强的表演性。但有些自恋的
folks are very selfish lovers the sex
人是非常自私的情人，他们的性爱
can be a little bit porny like it's a
可能有点像色情片，有点
bit you know like a bit over the top and
过火，就像
like I said it feels performative and um
我说的，感觉像是在表演。
but for some people where it gets into
但对一些人来说，
Dangerous Waters is when people are
危险之处在于，当人们处于自恋型
narcissistic relationships and they feel
关系中时，他们感觉自己
like they're having sex just to go along
只是为了
just to keep the trains of the
维持
relationship going along and that's a
关系而做爱，这是一种
very unhealthy precedent so it can be on
非常不健康的模式。所以，这可能介于一种
a spectrum from sort of ridiculous
荒谬的
performative sex to maybe they're
表演型性爱和他们
skilled that they want to sort of show
想要解决的性技巧之间。
off but then they're like a little
他们喜欢炫耀，但又像个
six-year-old who wants to get a lollipop
六岁的小孩，做了什么好事就想要根棒棒糖。
and then all the way up to stuff that
然后，他们甚至会做出一些
feels almost coercive Superman has
近乎胁迫的事情。超人有氪石，
Kryptonite and in the context of the
在
Superman story Kryptonite is the thing
超人的故事里，氪石是超人过敏的东西，是能
thing that kind of you know defeats his
削弱他
very strong set of powers for a
强大力量的东西。那么，对于
narcissist what is their Kryptonite what
自恋者来说，他们的“氪石”是什么？是什么
is the thing that you know makes them
让他们
fall to their knees and that they run
屈服，让他们
from when they see it in a person a
看到这种
trait
特质就逃之夭夭？
maybe I think that for a narcissistic
我认为，对于自恋
person there's a couple of ways
者来说，“
Kryptonite can show up I think that the
氪石”可以以几种方式出现。我认为，
Kryptonite that we could bring into it
我们可以引入的“氪石”
is not engaging with them anymore right
是不再与他们互动，不再让他们获得
not giving them the satisfaction of the
战斗的快感，不再和
fight not getting into the mud with them
他们纠缠不清。
we have to be strong in the face of that
我们必须坚强地面对他们，
because they're going to want the fight
因为他们会想要战斗，
so they're going to push and they're
所以他们会不断地挑衅、攻击、反击。 他们会
going to push and they're going to push
不断地挑衅，
and push and try to poke us and make us
试图激怒我们，逼我们
take the fight because they're really
反击，因为他们真的很
good at fighting another thing that's
擅长战斗。
Kryptonite for a narcissistic person is
对自恋者来说，最大的克星就是
than them because they they do feel they
比他们强大得多的人，因为他们会
sort of feel cowed by them so if they me
感到被对方压制。
like I said I gave you the example of
就像我刚才举的例子，一个
person working in a large organization
在大公司工作的中层自恋者，
and then they meet the big CEO and it's
然后遇到了公司的大CEO。如果这位CEO
really really great if you had one of
很有同理心，那就更好了。
narcissistic person who's almost trying
自恋者想方设法
to get into the good books with this
讨好这位
empathic CEO and all their usual tricks
富有同理心的CEO，但他们惯用的伎俩
aren't working that would definitely a
都不管用。这绝对也是他们的克星之一。
the very person that they Envy wants
他们嫉妒的人想要
them to be sort of warm and fuzzy and
他们表现得热情友好，而这正是
all the things that they have contempt
他们所鄙视的。
for but I have to say not engaging with
但我必须说，不去理会自恋
a narcissistic person is the ultimate
者才是终极
Kryptonite and not sort of oooing and
克星，而不是对他们投以羡慕的
eyeing narcissistic people are very used
目光。 自恋的人很习惯
to people oooing and eyeing over them
别人对他们发出赞叹和注视。
what about authentic
那么，真实的自我呢？
I saw you talk about that once that they
我之前看到你谈到过，他们
don't like people that are authentic
不喜欢真实的人，
they feel threatened by people who are
会觉得受到威胁。
authentic so and to show up as your
所以，
authentic self in a narcissistic
在一段自恋的关系中展现真实的自我
relationship can actually be say
实际上可能很
dangerous I put dangerous in quotes it's
危险。我给“危险”加了引号。
not like they're going to beat you up
他们不会真的打你，
but they're not going to have it right
但他们不会接受
your true self your authentic self
你真实的自我，
they're going to mock it they're going
他们会嘲笑你，会
to have contempt for it they're going to
鄙视你。
if if you're not solid in that authentic
如果你不够坚定，
identity they're going to attempt to
他们就会试图
dismantle it which is why many people
摧毁你的真实自我。这就是为什么很多人在
struggle if they don't know they're
不了解自己
dealing with a narcissistic person they
面对的是自恋者的情况下，很难在
may struggle with authenticity in a
一段自恋的
narcissistic relationship because it
关系中保持真实，因为真实自我很容易被
gets dismantled it's hard enough for us
摧毁。我们本来就很难做到
to get to authenticity if somebody wants
真实，如果有人想要
to dismantle it especially when we're
摧毁它，尤其是在我们
younger I think authenticity the odds of
年轻的时候，那就更难了。我认为，
it happening grow with age it's young
随着年龄的增长，保持真实的可能性也会增加。年轻的时候，做真实的自己
it's hard to be a young authentic person
很难。 做一个年轻真实的人，
but if you remain solid in your
但如果你在自恋的人
authentic identity around the
面前始终保持真实的自我，
narcissistic person they'll actually
他们很可能会
probably get bored and leave which is
感到厌倦然后离开，这当然是
always the Hope right they may ramp up
希望所在。他们可能会兴奋
for a little while but then that you're
一阵子，但之后你对
just not an interesting Target to them
他们来说就不再是有趣的目标了，
anymore so then they'll sort of slowly
所以他们会慢慢
lose interest and walk away famous
失去兴趣，然后离开。名人
narcissists what what what famous people
自恋者？什么？名人都是这样？
are oh [__] you think all famous people
哦，天哪，你以为所有名人都是这样吗？我
are I don't think all are but I think a
不认为所有名人都是，但我认为
lot are because the Quest for fame is a
很多都是，因为追求名利是一种
very narcissistically driven interest
非常自恋的兴趣，对吧？
right so I think most normal people
所以我认为大多数普通人
don't want to be famous they really
并不想出名，他们真的
don't if you talk to average per person
不想。如果你问问普通人，
do you want to be famous like hell no I
你想出名吗？当然不想！我
want to be able to go to the grocery
想去
store and have no one know who I am I
超市买东西，没人认识我。我
without being recognized so I think we
想过自己的生活，不被人认出来。所以，如果我们
talk famous people you're saying that is
谈论名人，你说
it one in five one in six seems like a
五分之一？六分之一？这听起来很多。
lot I'd say famous people we at 40 to
我认为
50% 40 to 50% of famous people I do I
名人占40%到50%。 我
really think it's a coin flip what about
觉得这完全是五五开，
world leaders now we're we might be
现在的世界领导人呢？我们可能更
closer to 60 to 70% I mean think of what
接近60%到70%。想想
you're signing up for it's crazy I need
你签的是什么合同，这太疯狂了。我需要
to run a country I believe I can run a
治理一个国家，我相信我能治理好一个
country and you know what there's we
国家。你知道吗，
have in over history had some good
纵观历史，确实有一些优秀的
people do that but when you look at the
人做到了这一点。但当你看到如今的
circus politics has become which is
政治，它变成了一场
performative and ridiculous and
作秀，荒谬可笑，夸夸其谈，残酷无情，充满
bombastic and cruel and critical and
批判和
manipulative I don't see how someone
操控。我不明白一个
non-narcissistic could ever win at that
不自恋的人怎么可能在这种
game why do we vote for narcissists why
游戏中获胜。我们为什么要投票给自恋者？为什么要把
do we put them into Power well I mean I
他们送上权力宝座？我的意思是，我
think that we we we're still we still do
认为我们仍然在做
what I call we or many of us call we
我所说的，或者我们很多人所说的，我们
still Fawn in their in their in the face
仍然在迎合他们的
of their Charisma I think we believe
魅力。我认为我们仍然相信
somebody who walks around thinking that
那些到处走来走去，自以为无所不能的人。
have the goods I still think we fall for
我认为我们仍然会被那些只会
the circus Barker we fall for the person
夸夸其谈的人所蒙蔽，我们会被那些
who is who is sort of selling the story
兜售故事的人所迷惑。
we we we vote for them we choose them
我们投票给他们，我们选择他们。
and I think we want you know this is the
我想我们想让你明白，这是
best example I can give you Stephen when
我能给你举的最好的例子，斯蒂芬。当
we go to a magic show right I don't know
我们去看魔术表演的时候，对吧？我不知道
if you've ever been to a magic show this
你有没有去过
place called The Magic Castle in La you
洛杉矶一个叫“魔术城堡”的地方，
should you should try to go sometime
你应该找个时间去看看，
because I find it intriguing but when
因为我觉得很吸引人。但是当
you go there's no there's no such thing
你真正去看的时候，你会发现根本没有所谓的
as magic it's all slight of hand right
魔法，一切都只是手法而已。
but for a moment we I don't want them to
但那一刻，我们不想让他们
show me the trick I want to be lost in
告诉我魔术的原理，我想沉浸在
the magic and most of us most of us not
魔术的氛围中。我们大多数人——当然不是所有人，
all I think some people want to know how
有些人想知道
the trick is done but once we're shown
魔术是怎么做到的——但是一旦魔术的原理揭晓，
how the trick is done the magic's gone
魔法就消失了，剩下的只是技巧而已。对吧？
right most people don't want to know how
大多数人并不想知道魔术的原理，
the trick is done we want to believe in
我们只想相信
magic and that's why narcissistic people
魔法的存在。这就是为什么自恋的人
don't get called out because there's
不会被揭穿的原因，因为他们
something about them there's something
身上有一种特质，一种
feels you know there's a confidence they
他们
breed because they have so much
散发出的自信，因为他们非常
conviction but it's misplaced conviction
自信，但这是一种错位的自信。
or Integrity it's just they just believe
他们并非出于事实或正直的信念，只是
it because they think it's true and it's
因为他们认为这是真的，而且这有利于
going to forward their cause so that
他们的事业，所以就盲目相信。这
becomes a selfing exactly but we believe
完全是一种自我膨胀。但我们相信
most of us don't have that kind of
大多数人都没有这种
conviction we doubt ourselves we
信念，我们会怀疑自己，会
question ourselves and so when someone
质疑自己。所以，当有人带着
comes in with absolute 100% I wanted to
百分之百的绝对信念出现时，
conviction we're like wow then they must
我们就会惊叹：“哇，那他们
really know what they're talking about
肯定很懂行。”
leaders have conviction but in fact when
领导者需要信念。但事实上，当
we see a leader who's circumspect who
我们看到一位谨慎的领导者，比如他
might say well give me a minute I want
说“给我一分钟，我想
to weigh both sides of this those
权衡一下”，这些
leaders are often viewed as more
领导者往往被认为
weak-minded and are less likely often to
意志薄弱，更难
get the vote if our adversary in another
获得选票。如果我们在另一个
country is a narcissist you know like a
国家的对手是个自恋狂，比如
Putin or I know Kim Jong whatever he's
普京或者金正恩（不管他
called um would we rather our leader
叫什么），我们难道希望
that's against him be a narcissist as
反对他的领导人也是个自恋狂吗？
well that's a fantastic question do we
这真是个好问题。我们真的
want a narcissist fighting a narcissist
希望一个自恋狂对抗另一个自恋狂吗？
I would say
我的答案是：
that the problem with a narcissist
自恋者之间
fighting a narcissist is that they lose
争斗的问题在于，他们会忽略
track of what is good for their people
民众的利益，
MH so they could drag them into a
从而可能将他们拖入
conflict or a problem that could harm
冲突或问题中，造成
the populace economically physically
经济、人身、
battles Wars the whole nine yards right
战争等各种损害。
and that's what a narcissistic person is
自恋者
more likely to do because they can't be
更容易这样做，因为他们无法
the smaller one in the fight it's all
在争斗中处于弱势，一切都取决于自我，这是
about e it's two egos fighting each
两个自尊心在较量，
other they can't just say okay no but an
他们无法轻易妥协。一个
overly empathic leader might do a little
过度同理心的领导者或许会尝试
bit of saying okay and then a
说“好的”，但
narcissistic or a psychopathic leader
自恋或精神病态的领导者
will absolutely sort of railroad that
绝对会压制对方。我们真正需要的是一个
person that sort of perfect midlevel
完美的中层领导者，既睿智
circumspect aware of the needs of the
谨慎，了解民众的需求，
populace but aware of the psychology of
又了解施暴者的心理。说实话，
to say if I ran the world Stephen and I
如果我能统治世界，斯蒂芬，我甚至
don't not even even long shot and I wish
不敢奢望，我希望
I was more grandiose because really my
自己更有远见，因为
career would be fire if I was but I'm
如果我有远见，我的事业将会非常成功。但我
not and so but I wish what one place I
没有，所以我希望…… 我真心
wish we really brought more narcissism
希望我们能将更多关于自恋的
training is into di diplomacy I wish
培训融入外交领域。我希望
more of the diplomats around the planet
世界各地的外交官、
secretaries of state and un
国务卿和联合国
Representatives understood narcissism
代表都能了解自恋，
because I think a lot of times people
因为我认为很多时候人们
are making bad deals where a lot of
达成了糟糕的协议，
people are getting hurt and they're
伤害了很多人，他们
trying to negotiate with people you
试图与那些根本无法谈判的人谈判。
cannot negotiate with anyone who's ever
任何
tried to negotiate with a narcissistic
尝试过与自恋的
spouse knows that it's impossible it's
配偶谈判的人都知道这是不可能的，
no different with a world leader and I
与世界领导人谈判也一样。我
think a lot of innocent people have been
认为，当
incredibly harmed as we diddle around
我们犹豫不决地
and try to negotiate with narcissistic
试图与自恋的
world leaders and just simply aren't
世界领导人谈判，却又
willing to call them out for what they
不愿意指出他们的真面目时，许多无辜的人受到了极大的伤害。
are what is the most important thing we
我们
haven't discussed that we should have
尚未讨论但应该
discussed I would say the most important
讨论的最重要的事情是什么？我认为
thing that we've discussed is that I
我们讨论过的最重要的事情是，我
don't want people to leave this
不希望人们带着悲观绝望的心情离开这次
conversation thinking it's all doom and
谈话。
gloom people can take themselves back
人们可以
from these relationships this isn't like
从这些关系中解脱出来，这并非某种
sort of some terrible deterministic
可怕的
destiny that I've been through a
宿命。我也经历过一段
narcissistic relationship so I'm never
自恋的关系。 我永远不可能做到
going to be authentic I think what's
真实。我认为最令人惊讶的
remarkable is once people learn about
是，一旦人们了解了
this and they're taught about this and
这一点，并被教导了这一点以及
the Dynamics of it and they're given
其中的动态，他们就会改变。 当他们被
permission to call abusive Behavior what
允许直呼虐待行为的本质时，
it is they're able to slowly but surely
他们就能缓慢但坚定地
start coming back into themselves no
开始找回自我，
longer shaming themselves for having a
不再因为自己的
need or a want or a feeling or a hope
需求、愿望、感受或希望而感到羞耻。
people do heal and I've seen remarkable
人们确实能够疗愈，我见过许多令人动容的
stories of people coming back from
故事，人们从
familial narcissistic abuse marital
家庭自恋型人格虐待、婚姻
narcissistic abuse long-term commit
自恋型人格虐待、长期承诺关系中的
relationship narcissistic abuse
自恋型人格虐待、
workplace narcissistic abuse and out of
职场自恋型人格虐待中走出来，变得
it have come out so much wiser stronger
更加睿智、坚强，
finally enacting their creative selves I
最终展现出他们富有创造力的自我。我
really want people to leave this episode
真心希望大家在听完这期节目后，能够
knowing all the Dynamics but that not
了解所有相关的动态，
only is healing possible it happens all
不仅明白疗愈是可能的，而且它一直在发生，
the time to people but it's work and
但这需要付出努力，并
it's not an easy
非易事。
process if you've seen my most recent
如果你看过我最近
post on LinkedIn you probably have seen
在LinkedIn上的帖子，你可能已经注意到，
that I'm on a bit of a hiring spree at
我
the moment across my company flight
目前正在我的公司Flight
group trying to find the world's best
Group进行大规模招聘，努力寻找全球顶尖
talent and throughout these years of
人才。多年来，在
build building these businesses my first
创建这些企业的过程中，我
Port of Call for hiring has always been
招聘的首选平台始终是
LinkedIn jobs who are a proud sponsor of
LinkedIn Jobs，他们也是
this podcast this is because of two
本播客的赞助商。这主要有两个
reasons number one LinkedIn isn't just
原因： 首先，LinkedIn 不仅仅是
another job board it has a vast network
一个招聘网站，它拥有
of more than a billion professionals and
超过十亿专业人士和
quality candidates which I believe makes
优质候选人的庞大网络，我认为这使它成为
it the best place to find in higher
寻找其他任何地方都找不到的高级专业人才的最佳平台。
else and number two their process and
其次，LinkedIn 的流程和
features LinkedIn is constantly finding
功能不断改进，使其
ways to make the hiring process easier
招聘流程
with super easy and intuitive features
更加便捷直观。
hiring is easy when you have that many
拥有如此多的
quality candidates in in fact 86% of
优质候选人，招聘就变得轻而易举。事实上，86% 的
small businesses get a qualified
小型企业都能
candidate within 24 hours through
在 24 小时内通过
Linkedin jobs post your job for free at
LinkedIn Jobs 找到合适的候选人。
doac that's linkedin.com
立即访问 linkedin.com
doac to post your job for free right now
免费发布您的职位。
and of course terms and conditions apply
当然，条款和条件适用。
we have a closing tradition where the
我们有一个结束语，
last guest leaves a question for the
最后一位嘉宾会给下一位嘉宾留下一个问题。
next guest oh in the Diary of a CEO not
哦，在 CEO 的日记里，
knowing who they're leaving it
他们并不知道问题会留给谁。
for the question here that's been left
留给你的问题是：
which was your darkest day and how did
你人生中最黑暗的一天是什么时候？
you turn the lights
你是如何振作起来的？
on I was stalked by someone who went who
我曾被一个跟踪狂跟踪，后来他
sexually assaulted me and um it was sort
性侵了我，那简直是一场
of this nightmarish Collegiate
噩梦。大学
Experience before you would report these
经历，在人们举报这些事情之前……我……我年纪也
older than you and it was it was
大了不少。 比你想象的还要
horrific I it was just absolutely
可怕，简直太
horrific and there was I didn't
可怕了。我当时根本不
understand I talk about not knowing what
明白，我根本不知道什么
narcissism was I was was I was much
是自恋。那时候我还很
younger as I'm still my teens early 20s
年轻，十几岁到二十出头。
um but you that one experience you
但是，那一次经历让我深刻体会到创伤对
to us but I it was it was absolute
我们造成的影响。那真是极度的
Terror I was being stalked all the time
恐惧。我一直被人跟踪，不
I didn't know what to do we didn't
知道该怎么办。我们当时
understand this stuff then we did not
不了解这些，
understand we did not talk about it it
也不谈论这些。那时候还
was we didn't have cell phones it was
没有手机，还是
dialing phones days and the person just
拨号电话的年代。那个人不断地
kept Breaking Me Down breaking me down I
摧毁我，让我崩溃。我
didn't know what I was dealing with I
不知道自己到底在面对什么，我
didn't have a lot of self self-esteem I
非常自卑，
didn't know who to ask and you know it
不知道该向谁求助。你知道，
was sort of and then it was um yeah it
当时的情况就是这样。嗯，就是这样。
was what it was and so probably is what
或许正是这段经历促使
propelled me to want to work with people
我想要帮助那些被
who are doubted by systems and who are
体制质疑的人，帮助
to help me want understand trauma A
他们理解创伤。一个
system that doubted you there was
质疑你的体制。
nowhere to go with that stuff to this
直到
day when women bring um
今天，当女性举报大学校园
reports of sexual assault or abuse on
性侵或虐待时，
campuses they're they're believed
她们的遭遇仍然无处可去。她们的遭遇往往不被相信，
they're not believed more often than
不被相信的次数远多于被
they are believed they're blamed there
相信的次数，她们还会遭到指责。
wasn't even a I didn't even know where
我甚至不知道该去哪里，
to go I didn't know where to take it I
不知道该把这件事告诉谁，也不
didn't know who to tell it's fine I mean
知道该告诉谁。没关系，我的意思是，
I I when I say it's fine i' like I've
当我说没关系的时候，我
done the work I've been supported
做了些努力，接受了心理
through therapy but you just didn't know
治疗，但你就是不知道
where to take it with they an narcissist
该把这件事告诉谁。那个施暴者是个自恋狂，我当时和他/她并不熟。当时，我
that person who did it I didn't know
认识他/她，只是泛泛之交。是的，我肯定地
known to me yes for sure I say
说，他/她是个
vulnerable narcissist actually which I
脆弱的自恋者，实际上，我
think by far even some ways is com is at
认为他/她在某些方面甚至与
malignant narcissistic person and in
恶性自恋者的危险程度不相上下。在
that time Stephen very frankly like
那段时间里，斯蒂芬，坦率地说，就像
doing this work I don't know what your
做这份工作一样，我不知道你
experience has been as a public person
作为公众人物的经历如何，
but maybe as a woman woman of color it's
但也许作为一名女性，尤其是有色人种女性，情况是这样的……
it's a little more risk is that I've had
风险确实更大一些，因为我曾
me in online spaces and issue some real
在网上听到过一些非常危险的话，甚至有人对我发出真正的威胁，
and it all came back at me in fact we
而这些威胁最终都反噬了我。事实上，
last few years and it just it flooded me
过去几年里就发生过类似的事情，它彻底淹没了我。
I I'd really compartmentalized that
我之前一直努力把那段
piece and it was um and it all comes
经历隔离开来，但当
something like that when you felt again
你再次经历类似的事情时，所有的一切都会涌上心头。那时，骚扰
back then it wasn't online stocking it
不是在网上进行的，而是
was using phones it was following you
通过手机进行的，有人跟踪你，
places my things were being stolen it
我的东西被偷了，他们还对我进行煤气灯操纵，
was a lot of gaslighting my things would
我的东西被偷了，
be stolen then my things would be put
然后又被放了
back so the campus police didn't believe
回去。所以校园警察不相信
me they'd said you said your stuff was
我，他们说：“你说你的东西
so stolen but your backpack is right
被偷了，但你的背包明明就在
there but the person would take my
那里。”但那个人会拿走我的
backpack and then put the backpack back
背包，然后再把它放回
in its place can I ask how did that end
原处。我可以问问这件事最终是怎么解决的吗？
um I left the
我离开了
university is is that why you left the
大学。这就是你离开
UN has that inspired why you were
联合国的原因吗？这件事是否影响了你
focused on working on this subject
专注于这个领域的研究？
matter at all no no I I I think I'm like
不，不，我想我和
most people should try my I I don't mean
大多数人一样，应该尝试……我不是想
to laugh about it but I
嘲笑它，但我确实把它
compartmentalized it you know and I'm
隔离开了。 我知道，我的
saying like as we mostly dissociate from
意思是，就像我们大多数时候都会与
our pain and so um consciously it's uh
痛苦分离一样，所以，嗯，有意识地……不，
no not consciously I think dissociation
不是有意识地。我认为分离
is a very protective mechanism I think
是一种非常有效的保护机制。
when we've gone through trauma I think
我认为，当我们经历创伤时，身心会以某种方式运作。
protect us um I think the mind is also
我认为身体很奇妙，它会试图保护我们。嗯，我认为心灵也在
trying to protect us and together like
试图保护我们。
these these are painful things but the
这些都是痛苦的事情，但
problem is them getting pushed away
问题是，
actually doesn't do us any favors if you
如果我们把它们推开，实际上对我们没有任何好处，
will you know what I'm saying and so um
你知道我的意思吗？所以，嗯，是的，
yeah well thank you thank you for um
谢谢你，谢谢你
taking the time to write such brilliant
花时间写出如此精彩
important books on a subject that is
重要的书，探讨一个
still not welln enough H in the way that
仍然没有得到充分理解的主题。
you go about both your videos your
你制作视频、创作
content more broadly but especially your
内容（更广泛地说）的方式，尤其是你的
books is so important because you're
书，都非常重要，因为你以一种
giving information in a very very
非常
accessible way and information is always
易于理解的方式提供信息。信息
and awareness is always the first step
和意识永远是改变
situation and there must be so many
现状的第一步。肯定有
thousands hundreds of thousands of
成千上万、数十万人、
people millions of people that have been
数百万人
exposed to your work it's heightened
接触过你的作品，它提高了
their awareness and because of that
他们的意识，正因如此。
they've taken a step out of a situation
他们已经摆脱了对
that wasn't serving them that was
他们毫无益处、
hurting their health and happiness and
损害他们身心健康和幸福的处境，
towards a better place and that is a
走向了更好的未来，这真的是一件
really remarkable thing that is a really
了不起的事情，真的非常了不起。
really remarkable thing this book was um
这本书……嗯，
I've heard about the word narcissism but
我听说过“自恋”这个词，但这本
this new book it's not you turn the
新书真的让我
lights on for me in a really really
茅塞顿开，说
important way to be honest as well as a
实话，它对我作为一名
CEO as a business leader it also made me
CEO和商业领袖来说意义非凡。它也让我开始反思
um ask myself a lot of questions about
自己的很多
myself about behavior that I have I
行为。我
don't consider myself to be a narcissist
不认为自己是自恋者，
but but as I was reading about the
但是当我读到关于
behaviors of narcissists and also the
自恋者的行为以及它对
impact that it can have on someone I
人的影响时，我
thought [__] hell like you
心想，我的天哪，就像
know it's um as you said it's Insidious
你说的，
it's Insidious and we I think I'm right
它很阴险，很阴险。我想我
in saying that we can all
说得没错，我们有时都会
exhibit some traits of narcissism
表现出一些自恋的特征，
sometimes and we kind of you know Define
我们有时会把
that as being an our or whatever um and
它定义为……嗯，
it really made me want to be a better
它真的让我想要成为一个更好的
person it really really did really made
人，真的真的让
me want to be a much much better person
我想要…… 成为一个更好的人，
so thank you for that thank you for
所以非常感谢你，感谢你
shining a light on this subject matter
关注这个话题，
and thank you for all the millions of
感谢
people that you've helped through your
你通过你的工作帮助了数百万人，
work it's really important I love that I
这真的很重要，我喜欢这一点。我的
I mean I think that that's such an
意思是，我认为这是一个非常
interesting take on is that we do
有趣的观点，那就是我们
sometimes do these things that are
有时会做一些
narcissistic but we you know not even
自恋的事情，但你知道，这甚至不是
because we are narcissistic but to even
因为我们自恋，而是为了
recalibrate those behaviors I think the
重新调整这些行为。我认为，
the the better we all can be the more
我们越能变得更好，
we're fortified should someone who has
我们就越强大，即使
these qualities come into our life that
生活中出现了拥有这些品质的人，
we don't give up on ourselves and I
我们也不会放弃自己。我
think that that's the more good we can
认为，我们能
sort of create in our univers is that
在我们的世界里创造的美好越多，
the bad's going to happen it's the
坏事就会发生，这是
nature of life but we'll be stronger in
生活的本质，但我们会变得更强大，
the face of it so thank
所以非常感谢
you I think it was about a year ago I
你。我想大约一年前，我
became obsessed with sleep to the point
开始痴迷于睡眠，以至于
that as many of you know I pretty much
你们很多人都知道，睡眠对我来说几乎是
have it as a non-negotiable one of the
不可妥协的。
things that I found is a brand called
我发现了一个名为
Eight sleep that sponsor this podcast
Eight Sleep的品牌，他们赞助了这个播客。
and that is the cover that I have on my
我
bed some of you will know that in order
床上的被子，你们有些人可能知道，
to have sleep our bodies need to be a
为了睡个好觉，我们的体温需要达到
certain temperature and there's slight
一定的标准，而每个人的体温都略有
variance between all of us that's
不同。
exactly what eight sleep does it
八点睡眠（Eight Sleep）正是利用了这一点，它能让我们
learns more energized and more capable
精力更充沛，更有能力
to pursue our goals the podcast sponsors
去追求目标。我的播客赞助商都是
that I have are brands that I love and
我喜爱并
use and eight sleep is one of them I've
使用的品牌，八点睡眠就是其中之一。
in my life and eight sleep is certainly
我的生活经历了很多科技变革，八点睡眠无疑是其中之一。
one of them check it out at eight
访问 eightsleep.com 了解更多信息。
[Music]
[音乐]
savings
优惠
o
o